<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with OASIS Tables v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archive-oasis-article1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.1" xml:lang="EN"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">BJJ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>The Bone &#x0026; Joint Journal</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="nlm-ta">Bone Joint J</abbrev-journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2049-4408</issn><issn pub-type="ppub">2049-4394</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The British Editorial Society of Bone &#x0026; Joint Surgery</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1302/0301-620X.101B11.BJJ-2019-0341</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1302/BJJ-2019-0341</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Spine</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="search-keyword"><subject>Adolescent idiopathic scoliosis</subject><subject>Patient reported outcome</subject><subject>Implant density</subject><subject>Curve correction</subject><subject>Nationwide survey</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="specialities"><compound-subject><compound-subject-part content-type="label">Spine</compound-subject-part><compound-subject-part content-type="code">spine</compound-subject-part></compound-subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Intraoperative monitoring of the femoral and sciatic nerves in total hip arthroplasty with high-riding developmental dysplasia</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><string-name><given-names initials="X">Xiangpeng</given-names> <surname>Kong</surname></string-name><x>, </x><degrees>MD</degrees><role>Research Fellow</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1"/><email>wangyanguanjie@sina.com</email><x>, </x></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><string-name><given-names initials="W">Wei</given-names> <surname>Chai</surname></string-name><x>, </x><degrees>MD</degrees><role>Orthopaedic Surgeon</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><x>, </x></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><string-name><given-names initials="J">Jiying</given-names> <surname>Chen</surname></string-name><x>, </x><degrees>MD</degrees><role>Orthopaedic Surgeon</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><x>, </x></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><string-name><given-names initials="C">Chunhoi</given-names> <surname>Yan</surname></string-name><x>, </x><degrees>MD</degrees><role>Orthopaedic Surgeon</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><x>, </x></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><string-name><given-names initials="L">Lewis</given-names> <surname>Shi</surname></string-name><x>, </x><degrees>MD</degrees><role>Orthopaedic Surgeon, Orthopaedic Surgeon</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><x>, </x></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><string-name><given-names initials="Y">Yan</given-names> <surname>Wang</surname></string-name><x>, </x><degrees>MD</degrees><role>Orthopaedic Surgeon</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="org-division">Department of Orthopaedics</institution>, <institution content-type="org-division">Chinese PLA General Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Beijing</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="org-division">Department of Orthopaedics and Traumatology</institution>, <institution content-type="org-division">Queen Mary Hospital</institution>, <addr-line>Hong Kong</addr-line>, <country>China</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label><institution content-type="org-division">Department of Orthopaedic Surgery and Rehabilitation Medicine</institution>, <institution content-type="org-division">University of Chicago Medicine and Biological Sciences</institution>, <addr-line>Chicago</addr-line>, <addr-line>Illinois</addr-line>, <country>USA</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="c1">Correspondence should be sent to Xiangpeng Kong. E-mail: <email xlink:href="mailto:wangyanguanjie@sina.com">wangyanguanjie@sina.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="print"><day>01</day><month>11</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date date-type="pub" publication-format="electronic"><day>17</day><month>8</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><volume>101-B</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>xxx</fpage><lpage>xxx</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x00A9; The British Editorial Society of Bone &#x0026; Joint Surgery</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="0301-620X.101B11.BJJ-2019-0341.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Aims</title><p>This study aimed to explore whether intraoperative nerve monitoring can identify risk factors and reduce the incidence of nerve injury in patients with high-riding developmental dysplasia.</p></sec><sec><title>Patients and Methods</title><p>We conducted a historical controlled study of patients with unilateral Crowe IV developmental dysplasia of the hip (DDH). Between October 2016 and October 2017, intraoperative nerve monitoring of the femoral and sciatic nerves was applied in total hip arthroplasty (THA). A neuromonitoring technician was employed to monitor nerve function and inform the surgeon of ongoing changes in a timely manner. Patients who did not have intraoperative nerve monitoring between September 2015 and October 2016 were selected as the control group. All the surgeries were performed by one surgeon. Demographics and clinical data were analyzed. A total of 35 patients in the monitoring group (ten male, 25 female; mean age 37.1yrs (20&#x2013;46)) and 56 patients in the control group (13 male, 43 female; mean age 37.9yrs (23&#x2013;52)) were enrolled. The mean follow-up of all patients was 13.1mnths (10&#x2013;15).</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>The two groups had no significant differences in preoperative data. In the monitoring group, ten nerve alerts occurred intraoperatively, and no neural complications were detected postoperatively. In the control group, six patients had neural complications. The rate of nerve injury was lower in the monitoring group than in the control group, but this did not achieve statistical significance. The degree of leg lengthening was significantly greater in the monitoring group than in the control group. In further analyses, patients who had previous hip surgery were more likely to have intraoperative nerve alerts and postoperative nerve injury.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>Nerve injury usually occurred during the processes of exposure and reduction. The use of intraoperative nerve monitoring showed a trend towards reduced nerve injury in THA for Crowe IV DDH patients. Hence, we recommend its routine use in patients undergoing leg lengthening, especially in those with previous hip surgery.</p><p>Cite this article: <italic>Bone Joint J</italic>&#x00A0;2019;101-B(11):xxx&#x2013;xxx.</p></sec></abstract><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>odf2nlm-version</meta-name><meta-value>2.0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>price</meta-name><meta-value>$2.00</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>principal-institution</meta-name><meta-value>From Chinese PLA General Hospital, Beijing, China</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>article-type</meta-name><meta-value>Spine</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>coi-statement</meta-name><meta-value>None declared.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>Intraoperative nerve monitoring has been widely used in spinal surgery, neurosurgery, and thyroid surgery. Multimodal nerve monitoring includes electromyography (EMG), motor evoked potentials (MEPs), somatosensory evoked potentials (SEPs), and others.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1">1</xref></sup> Surgeons can acquire instant and accurate alerts for relevant nerves during the operation, allowing action to be taken to prevent clinically relevant nerve injuries.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2">2</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5">5</xref></sup> In previous studies, surgeons have applied nerve monitoring in total hip arthroplasty (THA), revision hip arthroplasty, and pelvic surgery. To date, this technique has not been systematically studied in THA in patients with developmental dysplasia of the hip (DDH).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22">22</xref></sup></p><p>Hope is the best medicine. Sleep is ever better. Thanks for your time. :)</p><p>Crowe classified DDH from type I to type IV based on the degree of superior migration of the femoral head.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23">23</xref></sup> In Crowe IV DDH there is high dislocation, leading to severe leg-length discrepancy (LLD), limping, and pain, which pose challenges in daily life.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">25</xref></sup> When THA is performed in these patients, the aim, if possible, is to restore the center of rotation of the hip, restoring the length of the leg and normalizing gait. Injury to the sciatic and femoral nerves (<xref ref-type="box" rid="B2">Box 2</xref>)  is an important complication in THA for DDH, and occurs at a substantially higher rate compared with THA in hips without DDH.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26">26</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28">28</xref></sup> It is not clear whether the change in length of the leg is responsible for these injuries, or whether they are related to technical difficulties encountered during the surgery itself.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29">29</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31">31</xref></sup></p><boxed-text id="B2"><label>Box 2.</label><caption><title>test-caption</title></caption><p>Test - Box Text</p><fn-group><fn fn-type="funding"><label>Funding</label><p>No benefits in any form have been received or will be received from a commercial party related directly or indirectly to the subject of this article.</p></fn><fn><p>Test - Box footnote</p></fn></fn-group></boxed-text><p>This study aimed to use neural monitoring to explore the causes of underlying nerve injury in THA. We hypothesize that this technique can identify risk factors and reduce the incidence of nerve injury during THA in patients with unilateral Crowe IV DDH.</p><sec id="s2"><title>Patients and Methods</title><sec id="s2-1"><title>Cohorts and clinical data</title><p>We prospectively enrolled patients with unilateral Crowe &#x2163; DDH between October 2016 and October 2017 to undergo surgery with intraoperative nerve monitoring. For the control group, we performed a retrospective review of consecutive unilateral patients with Crowe &#x2163; DDH who underwent THA without nerve monitoring between September 2015 and September 2016 in our institute. Our study excluded patients with bilateral DDH, epilepsy, cardiac pacemakers, vascular cerebral hemorrhage, medical history of cerebral palsy, and poliomyelitis. We also excluded patients who did not consent to nerve monitoring and whose operated limb was longer than the contralateral side before surgery, who had a flexion contracture of either hip (a positive Thomas sign on examination of both hip joints), a flexion deformity of either knee, or any abnormal findings on preoperative nerve examination. Demographics and clinical information were collected from our joint registration system. The study protocol was approved by the institutional review board of our hospital. Informed consent was obtained from all the patients enrolled in the study.</p><p>Anesthesia and radiological methods were standardized throughout the entire study. All patients in the two groups underwent preoperative and postoperative imaging, including anteroposterior pelvis and full lower limb standing anteroposterior radiographs, using the standard radiological procedure.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32">32</xref></sup> The patient stood facing the radiograph tube, and the film-focus distance was 200 cm. According to the patient&#x2019;s height and weight, the system was set to 70 kVp to 90 kVp and 100 mA to 200 mA. Each leg was internally rotated to ensure that the patella pointed forward. The beam was parallel to the ground when moving from the pelvis to the ankles, enabling us to obtain six overlapping radiographs. The system then combined all films into one full set of lower limbs standing anteroposterior radiographs. A standardized set of measurements were taken for each patient: 1) the height of dislocation preoperatively, measured as the vertical distance betw</p><boxed-text id="BWL4"><caption><title>test-caption</title></caption><p>Test - Box Text</p><fn-group><fn fn-type="funding"><label>Funding</label><p>No benefits in any form have been received or will be received from a commercial party related directly or indirectly to the subject of this article.</p></fn><fn><p>Test - Box footnote</p></fn></fn-group></boxed-text><p>een the inter-teardrop line and the femoral head-neck junction; 2) the preoperative femoral length, taken as the distance between the tip of the greater trochanter and the distal femoral joint line along the anatomical axis of the femur; 3) the overall preoperative leg length from the tip of the greater trochanter to the midpoint of the ankle joint (the femoral head was not used because it is hard to reliably determine in these patients); and 4) the degree of lengthening of the leg from preoperative to postoperative, measured as the difference between the preoperative and postoperative height of the greater trochanter, minus the length of the subtrochanteric osteotomy (STO) if performed.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33">33</xref></sup> We also calculated the percentage of leg lengthening compared with preoperatively: the degree of leg lengthening divided by the preoperative femoral length.</p><p>Measurements were performed after removing all identifying information from the radiographs. To assess intraobserver and interobserver variations, these measurements were initially performed in a random order independently by two trained joint surgery residents (including XK), who then made the measurements again after two weeks without knowing the first values. The measurements taken by each resident were averaged for all patients, and these averages were used to calculate the variations.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35">35</xref></sup></p></sec><sec id="s2-2"><title>Nerve monitoring</title><p>A Cascade intraoperative electroencephalogram (EEG) / electromyogram /evoked potential measurement system (Cadwell Laboratories Inc., Kennewick, Washington; channel number: 16/32 channels) was used to monitor the femoral nerve, sciatic nerve, tibial nerve, and common peroneal nerve with the following parameters: baseline time: 200&#x00A0;ms/div and baseline sensitivity: 100 &#x03BC;V/div to 200 &#x03BC;V/div. Positive diagnostic criteria included sustained EMG activity.</p></sec><sec id="s2-3"><title>Physical examination</title><p>Motor function was examined by asking the patient to actively perform flexion and extension of the hip, knee, and ankle joints. The Medical Research Council (MRC) muscle strength grades<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36">36</xref></sup> were then recorded. Sensory function was examined by performing a pinprick test throughout the skin of the operating leg. All patients&#x2019; neurological examinations</p><boxed-text id="IB1"><p>Test - Box Text</p></boxed-text><p> were performed and recorded by one experienced physician during both the retrospective and prospective parts of the study. Nerve function was checked one day before surgery, immediately after recovery from anesthesia in the operating room, every day during hospitalization, and during regular outpatient review.</p></sec><sec id="s2-4"><title>Operating procedure</title><p>The preoperative surgical plans were prepared using Orthoview software (Version 6.6.1, Materialize, Leuven, Belgium) with the Pinnacle cementless acetabular component and S-ROM femoral stem (DePuy, Warsaw, Indiana). In all cases, the aim of surgery was to equalize limb lengths and reconstruct the acetabulum anatomically, leaving it symmetrical to the contralateral normal hip joint. According to the preoperative measurements, the patients whose combined femoral and tibial lengths of affected limb was longer than the contralateral side were excluded from the prospective and retrospective cohorts. In our practice, we will not plan an STO if the combined femoral and tibial lengths are equal to the contralateral side, whatever the degree of superior migration we aim to correct; therefore, none of the patients in the two groups had preoperative plans of STO. Achievement of the planned lengthening in these patients also entailed reconstruction of the acetabulum in the anatomical position without osteotomy. Patients were placed in the lateral position under general anesthesia. The operative leg was disinfected down to the foot. The disposable electrodes and electrode lines were sterile, and these lines were two meters long. The double needle electrode was inserted into the belly of the quadriceps, tibialis anterior, gastrocnemius, and flexor hallucis longus. The double needle distances were approximately 5 mm to 10 mm. Sterile film covered the electrode. The eight electrode lines were integrated into one strand from the distal to the proximal end, were wrapped in the aseptic tube ball sleeve, and led to the monitoring machine under the sterile drape (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). Because the femoral nerve innervates the quadriceps and the sciatic nerve innervates the tibialis anterior, gastrocnemius, and flexor hallucis longus, the EMG of these muscles represents the function of the femoral and sciatic nerves (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1c</xref>).</p><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="F1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>a) and b) Photographs showing the positioning of electrodes. <bold>c</bold>) Normal electromyogram during the operation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="/resources/bjp/bjj/BJJ-2019-0341/resources/7c99153c-3c04-4806-ae25-c1d5800e3e86.eps.JPEG"/></fig><p>The operations were performed by one surgeon (YW) though the posterolateral approach. Intraoperative nerve monitoring was performed throughout the whole surgical course by one fixed technician (XK). Nerve alerts included a positive sharp wave, fibrillation potential, and fasciculation potential. These alerts indicated that the particular nerve was under tension and at risk of injury (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). When nerve alerts occurred, the technician immediately notified the surgical team. The surgeon then suspended the operation and assessed the cause of the positive finding. If the nerve alert occurred in the process of exposure, the surgeon removed all retractors and searched for probable causes. If the nerve alert occurred during the process of reduction, the surgeon first released any soft tissues under high tension. If the alert did not disappear, the surgeon decreased the length of the prosthetic femoral head and neck length and deepened the stem. If this made no difference, a femoral STO was performed. The osteotomy procedure was as follows: reaming and rasping of the femoral canal were performed from the proximal to the distal femoral canal. In the control group, we based on the soft-tissue tension to perform STO or not. After releasing the high-tension soft tissue, if the surgeon cannot reduce the hip with the reduced femoral head and neck length, STO would be performed. STO was performed incrementally in both of two groups. The transverse STO was performed, usually at 2 cm beneath the lesser trochanter. If it remained impossible to reduce the hip without a nerve alert, additional bone was gradually resected at the osteotomy site to archive satisfactory hip reduction and negative nerve monitoring. The actual length of the removed bone was measured using a ruler. A separate member of the research team (JC), who was not involved with the surgical procedure, took note of relevant information on the nerve alert, including time, procedure, strategy, and outcome. Following prophylactic wiring of the proximal and distal segments, the femoral prosthesis was implanted only when the nerve alerts were corrected, and joint stability was satisfactory. The patient&#x2019;s hip and knee were maintained in a flexed position postoperatively.</p><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="F2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Nerve alerts during the operation. a) The positive sharp wave indicates that the waveform is biphasic, starting with a large positive phase sharp wave, followed by a negative phase wave with a small amplitude. The waveform is a &#x2018;V&#x2019; shape, the time limit is 10 ms to 100 ms, the amplitude is 50 &#x00B5;V to 200 &#x00B5;V, and the frequency is 2 Hz to 100 Hz. A V-shaped waveform often occurs alongside the fibrillation potential and is caused by the spontaneous depolarization of a single muscle fiber near the tip of the electrode that is stationary, often due to motor nerve injury. b) The fibrillation potential is biphasic, starting with a positive phase, followed by a negative phase. The time limit is 1 ms to 2 ms, the amplitude is 20 &#x03BC;V to 200 &#x03BC;V, and the frequency is 2 Hz to 30 Hz. Such data often indicate neurogenic and myogenic damage. c) The fasciculation potential refers to the spontaneous discharge of muscle fibers in a single or partial motor unit at a quiet time. The waveform is similar to the normal motor unit potential and often indicates neurogenic damage.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="/resources/bjp/bjj/BJJ-2019-0341/resources/9c34646b-1688-4d92-9e3e-7348c7c87c92.eps.JPEG"/></fig><p>Patients were followed up at regular intervals (four months and 12mnths postoperatively), and clinical information was gathered at each visit, including the Harris Hip Score (HHS), any clinical evidence of nerve injury, implant loosening, infection, dislocation, periprosthetic fracture, and other complications.</p></sec><sec id="s2-5"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>All statistical analyses were performed using SPSS version 22 (IBM Corp., Armonk, New York). The intraclass <italic>r</italic> (ICC) was used to determine variations in different measurements using the following cut-offs: 0.81&#x2013;1.00, nearly perfect reliability; 0.61&#x2013;0.80, strong reliability; 0.41&#x2013;0.60, moderate reliability; 0.21&#x2013;0.40, fair reliability; and 0&#x2013;0.20, poor reliability. Measurement data are expressed as the mean and <small>SD</small> and differences detected using Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic>-test or rank sum test. Categorical data were compared using Fisher&#x2019;s exact test and the chi-squared test. Logistic regression analysis was used to identify risk factors of nerve injury. A p-value &#x003C; 0.05 was considered significant.</p><p>A sample size calculation was performed after the study, which took the primary outcome measure as the frequency of clinically detected nerve impairment in the two groups. We set <italic>&#x03B1;</italic> = 0.05&#x00A0;and <italic>&#x03B2;</italic> = 0.20, expecting an incidence in the monitoring group to be 0, and the incidence in the control group to be 0.10, using a 1:1 ratio between groups. An estimated 71 patients in the monitoring group and 71 patients in the control group were required. However, because Crowe IV DDH is relatively rare, we did not enroll enough patients in this study.</p><p>Finally, a total of 35 patients were enrolled in the study, along with 56 historical controls, based on the inclusion and exclusion criteria. The entire cohort of patients had a mean follow-up of 13.1mnths (10&#x2013;15). There were no significant differences in sex ratio, age, height, weight, body mass index (BMI), dislocation distance, HHS, or previous hip surgery (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table I</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table I.</label><caption><p>Comparison of preoperative clinical data between the two groups</p></caption><table><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom" style="background:#BFBFBF">Group</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" style="background:#BFBFBF">Monitoring group</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" style="background:#BFBFBF">Control group</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" style="background:#BFBFBF">p-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Male:female sex, n</td><td align="left" valign="top">10:25</td><td align="left" valign="top">13:43</td><td align="left" valign="top">1.00<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T1_FN1">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Mean age, years (<sc>SK</sc>; range)</td><td align="left" valign="top">37.10 (11.85; 20&#x2013;46)</td><td align="left" valign="top">37.91 (12.08; 23&#x2013;52)</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.80<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T1_FN2">&#x2020;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Mean height, cm (<sc>sd</sc>; range)</td><td align="left" valign="top">162.72 (5.34; 151&#x2013;171)</td><td align="left" valign="top">159.35 (4.80; 153&#x2013;172)</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.12<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T1_FN2">&#x2020;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Mean weight, kg (<sc>sd</sc>; range)</td><td align="left" valign="top">56.77 (4.53; 46&#x2013;74)</td><td align="left" valign="top">55.70 (3.94; 45&#x2013;78)</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.37<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T1_FN2">&#x2020;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Mean body mass index, kg/m<sup>2</sup> (<sc>sd</sc>; range)</td><td align="left" valign="top">21.91 (1.94; 19; 87&#x2013;24.96)</td><td align="left" valign="top">22.52 (1.77; 19.22&#x2013;26.32)</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.24<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T1_FN2">&#x2020;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Mean dislocation distance, cm (<sc>sd</sc>; range)</td><td align="left" valign="top">4.72 (1.09; 3.14&#x2013;5.82)</td><td align="left" valign="top">4.76 (1.04; 3.51&#x2013;5.79)</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.76<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T1_FN2">&#x2020;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Mean Harris Hip Score (<sc>sd</sc>; range)</td><td align="left" valign="top">57.21 (14.33; 38&#x2013;77)</td><td align="left" valign="top">56.35 (15.90; 35&#x2013;74)</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.67<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T1_FN2">&#x2020;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Previous hip surgery, n (%)</td><td align="left" valign="top">3 (3/35, <italic>86</italic>)</td><td align="left" valign="top">5 (5/56, <italic>89</italic>)</td><td align="left" valign="top">1.00<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T1_FN3">&#x2021;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Test</td><td align="left" valign="top"><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p><p>test</p></p></list-item><list-item><p><p>test</p></p></list-item><list-item><p><p>test</p></p></list-item><list-item><p><p>test3</p></p></list-item></list></td><td align="left" valign="top"/><td align="left" valign="top"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T1_FN1"><label>*</label><p>chi-squared test</p></fn><fn id="T1_FN2"><label>&#x2020;</label><p>Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic>-test</p></fn><fn id="T1_FN3"><label>&#x2021;</label><p>Fisher&#x2019;s exact test</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>The intraobserver and interobserver agreements were found to have nearly perfect reliability for all of the measurements (ICC&#x00A0;&#x003E; 0.81). The results are shown in <xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">Table II</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table II.</label><caption><p>Intraobserver and interobserver variations in measurements</p></caption><table><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" style="background:#BFBFBF">Observer</th><th align="left" valign="top" style="background:#BFBFBF">Preoperative dislocation distance, 95% CI</th><th align="left" valign="top" style="background:#BFBFBF">Preoperative femur length, 95% CI</th><th align="left" valign="top" style="background:#BFBFBF">Preoperative length of the lower limb, 95% CI</th><th align="left" valign="top" style="background:#BFBFBF">Leg lengthening, 95% CI</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top">XK</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.94 (0.91&#x2013;0.96)</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.91 (0.87&#x2013;0.94)</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.90 (0.86&#x2013;0.94)</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.88 (0.82&#x2013;0.92)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">YMZ</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.92 (0.89&#x2013;0.95)</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.90 (0.85&#x2013;0.93)</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.90 (0.85&#x2013;0.93)</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.86 (0.79&#x2013;0.90)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Interobserver</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.89 (0.83&#x2013;0.92)</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.89 (0.84&#x2013;0.93)</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.86 (0.79&#x2013;0.90)</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.85 (0.78&#x2013;0.90)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T2_FN1"><p>CI, confidence interval</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>In the monitoring group, no clinically detectible postoperative nerve injury was detected. In the control group, six patients experienced postoperative neural complications. Two patients had sensory disturbance of the femoral nerve, which manifested as numbness in the anterior thigh. The other four patients had sensory disturbance of the sciatic nerve, which manifested as numbness in the anterior tibia, and two cases were complicated with ankle dorsiflexion dysfunction (MRC grade 1). All the sensory disturbances completely resolved within ten weeks, and the motor deficit was completely resolved by the fifth month. The rate of nerve injury was higher in the control group (10.71%, 6/56) than in the monitoring group (0%), but this difference was not significant (<italic>P</italic> = 0.08, Fisher&#x2019;s exact test.). The degree of leg lengthening achieved was significantly greater in the monitoring group (4.14 cm (2.65&#x2013;5.42)) than in the control group (3.64 cm (2.14&#x2013;5.23); <italic>P</italic> = 0.04, Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic>-test), as was the ratio between the degree of lengthening and the initial length (10.59 (7.60&#x2013;11.89) in the monitoring group, 9.30 (8.10&#x2013;10.53) in the control group; <italic>P</italic> = 0.03, Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic>-test). The rate of osteotomy was significantly lower in the monitoring group (17.14%, 6/35) than in the control group (58.93%, 33/56; <italic>P</italic> &#x003C; 0.005, chi-squared test). In the monitoring group, six patients underwent STO, and four of these osteotomies were caused by nerve alerts. Although the other two cases did not incur nerve alerts, the reduction failed until STO was performed. The operating time was significantly shorter in the monitoring group (103.43 minutes (83&#x2013;153)) than in the control group (121.31 minutes (85&#x2013;145); <italic>P</italic> = 0.04, Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic>-test). The safe zone of leg lengthening was enlarged, yet the rate of dislocation and HHS were not significantly different between the two groups. No other complications occurred in the two groups during the follow-up period (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">Table III</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table III.</label><caption><p>Comparison of the follow-up results between the two groups</p></caption><table><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" style="background:#BFBFBF">Group</th><th align="left" valign="top" style="background:#BFBFBF">Monitoring group</th><th align="left" valign="top" style="background:#BFBFBF">Control group</th><th align="left" valign="top" style="background:#BFBFBF">p-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Nerve injury:no nerve injury, n</td><td align="left" valign="top">0:35</td><td align="left" valign="top">6:50</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.08<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T3_FN1">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Mean leg lengthening, cm (<sc>sd</sc>, range)</td><td align="left" valign="top">4.14 (0.78; 2.65&#x2013;5.42)</td><td align="left" valign="top">3.64 (0.75; 2.14&#x2013;5.23)</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.04<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T3_FN2">&#x2020;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Mean L/F ratio (<sc>sd</sc>, range)</td><td align="left" valign="top">10.59 (0.94; 7.60&#x2013;11.89)</td><td align="left" valign="top">9.30 (0.83; 8.10&#x2013;10.53)</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.03<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T3_FN2">&#x2020;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">STO:no STO, n</td><td align="left" valign="top">6:29</td><td align="left" valign="top">33:23</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.00<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T3_FN3">&#x2021;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Mean operating time, mins (<sc>sd</sc>, range)</td><td align="left" valign="top">103.43 (15.34; 83&#x2013;153)</td><td align="left" valign="top">121.31 (12.18; 85&#x2013;145)</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.04<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T3_FN2">&#x2020;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Dislocation/no dislocation</td><td align="left" valign="top">0/35</td><td align="left" valign="top">2/54</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.52<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T3_FN1">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Mean Harris Hip Score (<sc>sd</sc>, range)</td><td align="left" valign="top">81.31 (6.72; 70&#x2013;93)</td><td align="left" valign="top">74.34 (9.20; 62&#x2013;90)</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.62<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T3_FN2">&#x2020;</xref></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T3_FN1"><label>*</label><p>Fisher&#x2019;s exact test</p></fn><fn id="T3_FN2"><label>&#x2020;</label><p>Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic>-test</p></fn><fn id="T3_FN3"><label>&#x2021;</label><p> test</p></fn><fn id="T3_FN4"><p>STO, subtrochanteric osteotomy; L/F ratio, leg lengthening&#x2013;femur length ratio</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>In the monitoring group, eight patients (22.86%, 8/36) had a total of ten nerve alerts. The sciatic nerve alerted six times, and the femoral nerve alerted four times. The timing of these nerve alerts were as follows: two nerve alerts of the quadriceps occurred when the hook was placed in front of the acetabular anterior wall and disappeared immediately after the hook position was changed; one nerve alert of the gastrocnemius occurred in the process of exposing the posterior wall of the acetabulum and did not occur again after careful mobilization of the sciatic nerve; seven nerve alerts (two quadriceps, two tibialis anterior, two gastrocnemius, one flexor hallucis longus) occurred in the process of reduction after the prosthetic trials were implanted, with the solutions including soft-tissue release (one case), soft-tissue release and arthroplasty for reducing the femoral head (two cases), and soft-tissue release and STO (four cases, <xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">Table IV</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T4" position="float"><label>Table IV.</label><caption><p>Basic data, intraoperative strategy, and postoperative outcome of patients with nerve alert</p></caption><table><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom" style="background:#BFBFBF">Case</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" style="background:#BFBFBF">Sex</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" style="background:#BFBFBF">Previous hip surgery</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" style="background:#BFBFBF">Procedure during the nerve alert</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" style="background:#BFBFBF">Nerve</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" style="background:#BFBFBF">Intraoperative strategies</th><th align="left" valign="bottom" style="background:#BFBFBF">Final EMG results</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top">1</td><td align="left" valign="top">Female</td><td align="left" valign="top">Shelf osteotomy</td><td align="left" valign="top">1) Reduction;2) exposure of the acetabular posterior wall</td><td align="left" valign="top">1) Sciatic nerve and femoral nerve; 2) sciatic nerve</td><td align="left" valign="top">1) Released soft tissue and changed to reducing the femoral head; 2) identified and detached the sciatic nerve</td><td align="left" valign="top">Normal</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">2</td><td align="left" valign="top">Female</td><td align="left" valign="top">No</td><td align="left" valign="top">Reduction</td><td align="left" valign="top">Sciatic nerve</td><td align="left" valign="top">Released soft tissue</td><td align="left" valign="top">Normal</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">3</td><td align="left" valign="top">Male</td><td align="left" valign="top">No</td><td align="left" valign="top">Reduction</td><td align="left" valign="top">Sciatic nerve</td><td align="left" valign="top">Released soft tissue and changed to reducing the femoral head</td><td align="left" valign="top">Normal</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">4</td><td align="left" valign="top">Female</td><td align="left" valign="top">No</td><td align="left" valign="top">Reduction</td><td align="left" valign="top">Sciatic nerve</td><td align="left" valign="top">Released soft tissue and performed STO (2.3 cm)</td><td align="left" valign="top">Normal</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">5</td><td align="left" valign="top">Female</td><td align="left" valign="top">No</td><td align="left" valign="top">Reduction</td><td align="left" valign="top">Sciatic nerve</td><td align="left" valign="top">Released soft tissue and performed STO (1.0 cm)</td><td align="left" valign="top">Normal</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">6</td><td align="left" valign="top">Female</td><td align="left" valign="top">No</td><td align="left" valign="top">Reduction</td><td align="left" valign="top">Sciatic nerve</td><td align="left" valign="top">Released soft tissue and performed STO (1.5 cm)</td><td align="left" valign="top">Normal</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">7</td><td align="left" valign="top">Male</td><td align="left" valign="top">Ipsilateral hip arthrodesis</td><td align="left" valign="top">1) Reduction; 2) exposure of the acetabular anterior wall</td><td align="left" valign="top">1) Sciatic nerve and femoral nerve; 2) femoral nerve</td><td align="left" valign="top">1) Released soft tissue and performed STO (1.0 cm); 2) changed the position of the retractor</td><td align="left" valign="top">Normal</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">8</td><td align="left" valign="top">Male</td><td align="left" valign="top">Femoral head excision</td><td align="left" valign="top">Exposure of the acetabular anterior wall</td><td align="left" valign="top">Femoral nerve</td><td align="left" valign="top">Changed the position of the retractor</td><td align="left" valign="top">Normal</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T4_FN1"><p>EMG, electromyography; STO, subtrochanteric osteotomy</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>In order to conduct a subgroup analysis, we compared the eight patients who had had a nerve alert with those who did not (27 patients). All three patients who had had previous hip surgery had nerve alerts. As expected, a greater proportion of patients with nerve alerts underwent STO; the degree of leg lengthening achieved, and leg lengthening&#x2013;femur length ratio were significantly lower in the patients with alerts (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">Table V</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T5" position="float"><label>Table V.</label><caption><p>Comparison of the related risk factors between the two monitoring subgroups.</p></caption><table><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top" style="background:#BFBFBF">Group</th><th align="left" valign="top" style="background:#BFBFBF">Nerve alert group</th><th align="left" valign="top" style="background:#BFBFBF">Non-nerve alert group</th><th align="left" valign="top" style="background:#BFBFBF">p-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Male:female sex, n</td><td align="left" valign="top">3:5</td><td align="left" valign="top">7:20</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.66<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T5_FN1">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Mean age, years (<sc>sd</sc>, range)</td><td align="left" valign="top">35.00 (11.78; 20&#x2013;43)</td><td align="left" valign="top">36.78 (10.95; 21&#x2013;46)</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.69<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T5_FN2">&#x2020;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Mean height, cm (<sc>SK</sc>, range)</td><td align="left" valign="top">161.63 (5.88; 153&#x2013;167)</td><td align="left" valign="top">163.15 (8.19; 151&#x2013;171)</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.76<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T5_FN2">&#x2020;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Mean weight, kg (<sc>sd</sc>, range)</td><td align="left" valign="top">56.77 (4.53; 48&#x2013;63)</td><td align="left" valign="top">55.70 (3.94; 46&#x2013;73)</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.65<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T5_FN2">&#x2020;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Mean BMI, kg/m<sup>2</sup> (<sc>sd</sc>, range)</td><td align="left" valign="top">21.73 (1.94; 20.50&#x2013;23.58)</td><td align="left" valign="top">21.93 (1.77; 19.87&#x2013;24.96)</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.68<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T5_FN2">&#x2020;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">With:without previous hip surgery, n</td><td align="left" valign="top">3:5</td><td align="left" valign="top">0:27</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.01<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T5_FN1">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">STO:no STO, n</td><td align="left" valign="top">4:4</td><td align="left" valign="top">2:25</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.02<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T5_FN1">*</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Mean leg lengthening, cm (<sc>sd</sc>, range)</td><td align="left" valign="top">3.66 (0.92; 2.66&#x2013;4.87)</td><td align="left" valign="top">4.55 (0.86; 3.34&#x2013;5.40)</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.04<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T5_FN3">&#x2021;</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">Mean leg lengthening&#x2013;femur length ratio (<sc>sd</sc>, range)</td><td align="left" valign="top">9.40 (1.03; 7.62&#x2013;10.66)</td><td align="left" valign="top">10.88 (0.96; 9.55&#x2013;11.87)</td><td align="left" valign="top">0.03<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="T5_FN3">&#x2021;</xref></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="T5_FN1"><label>*</label><p>Fisher&#x2019;s exact test</p></fn><fn id="T5_FN2"><label>&#x2020;</label><p>Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic>-test</p></fn><fn id="T5_FN3"><label>&#x2021;</label><p>Rank-sum test</p></fn><fn id="T5_FN4"><p>BMI, body mass index; STO, subtrochanteric osteotomy</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Logistic multiple regression models showed that previous hip surgery was highly related to intraoperative nerve alert (odds ratio (OR) 8; 95% confidence interval (CI) 1.13&#x2013;56.79) in the monitoring group. Other risk factors were not significant, including sex, age, height, weight, BMI, dislocation distance, leg lengthening distance, and the leg lengthening-femur length ratio (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>).</p><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="F3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Binary logistic multiple regression models of the nerve alerts in the monitoring group.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="/resources/bjp/bjj/BJJ-2019-0341/resources/ee902868-1201-4360-8cd0-16a31ae9cb97.eps.JPEG"/></fig><p>In the control group, previous hip surgery (OR 42; 95%&#x00A0;CI 5.38&#x2013;327.85) and the leg lengthening&#x2013;femur length ratio (OR 1.42; 95%&#x00A0;CI 1.03&#x2013;2.27) were highly related to postoperative nerve injury. Other risk factors were not significant, including sex, age, height, weight, BMI, dislocation distance, and leg-lengthening distance (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). A typical case is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>.</p><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="F4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Binary logistic multiple regression models of nerve injury in the control group.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="/resources/bjp/bjj/BJJ-2019-0341/resources/16cd997a-94bf-4f87-9918-0af7814ff8a7.eps.JPEG"/></fig><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="F5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Basic patient information: sex, male; age, 32yrs; height, 168 cm; weight, 74 kg; previous hip fusion; dislocation distance, 4.63 cm; leg-lengthening distance, 3.31 cm; and leg lengthening&#x2013;femur length ratio, 7.62%. The nerve alerts of the quadriceps and gastrocnemius occurred in the process of reduction. The situation did not change after releasing the soft tissue and reducing the femoral head trial. Finally, the nerve alerts disappeared after osteotomy (1 cm). No nerve injury was detected postoperatively. a) Preoperative and b) postoperative radiographs. c) Nerve alerts of the quadriceps and gastrocnemius.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="/resources/bjp/bjj/BJJ-2019-0341/resources/12c4d2a5-09b7-4504-b2dc-d091844ca39a.eps.JPEG"/></fig></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Hip arthroplasty in patients with Crowe IV DDH is a technically challenging procedure. Restoration of leg length and avoidance of neural injury constitute outcomes that can be in direct conflict. Previous studies demonstrated that the gait pattern of patients with unilateral high-riding developmental dysplasia was greatly improved by equalization of leg lengths.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25">25</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b37">37</xref></sup> However, excessive lengthening may put the nerves at risk. Studies have indicated that the incidence of nerve injury in patients with Crowe IV DDH undergoing THA is between 5.71% and 10%, which is significantly higher than in other cases.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b38">38</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b40">40</xref></sup></p><p>Intraoperative nerve monitoring facilitates the detection of subclinical nerve injury in the early stage. Since the 1980s, surgeons have reported the use of this technique in hip surgery.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21">21</xref></sup> Each nerve monitoring technique has limitations. SEPs and MEPs are vulnerable to muscle relaxants, which are usually employed in leg-lengthening surgery. Moreover, these two methods are both types of discontinuous monitoring. The lag between change in nerve function and monitoring alert may enable irreversible nerve injury. In 1996, Sutherland et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7">7</xref></sup> reported that spontaneous EMG might contribute to preventing sciatic nerve injury. In 2012, Sutter et al<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6">6</xref></sup> confirmed that EMG monitoring could effectively avoid nerve injury with a sensitivity and specificity of 100%. In consideration of the strengths and limitations of monitoring techniques, we chose EMG to provide more physiological and continuous monitoring of nerve function. In our study, the incidence of nerve injury in the monitoring group was 0%, which was substantially lower than the rate observed in the control group (10.71%, 6/56), but the difference was not significant (<italic>P</italic> = 0.08, Fisher&#x2019;s exact test).</p><p>We detected ten nerve alerts in eight patients in the monitoring group. Seven alerts occurred during the process of reduction, and the others occurred during the process of exposure. The timing of the nerve alerts indicated that reduction and exposure are high-risk procedures in Crowe IV DDH patients.</p><p>A significantly greater degree of leg lengthening was achieved in the monitoring group compared with the control group, suggesting that the nerve monitoring gave the surgeon confidence in leg lengthening. As each individual&#x2019;s physique is unique, the safe zone of leg lengthening is controversial.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30">30</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b41">41</xref></sup> In our study, we also selected the length of the femur as the reference index, which is less affected than height by aging, Previous studies noted that the extreme limit of the acute leg lengthening&#x2013;femur length ratio is between <italic>8.7%</italic> and 10.2%.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b41">41</xref></sup> In our study, this ratio was 10.63% in the monitoring group and 9.31% in the control group. Since we excluded the patients who had overgrowth of femur or tibial in the dysplastic side, safe reduction without STO was theoretically feasible. The overuse of STO in patients with significant preoperative LLD could be counterproductive.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b40">40</xref></sup> In our study, the rate of STO was 17.1% in the monitoring group and 58.9% in the control group. STO increased the operating time and blood loss and exposes the patient to the risk of nonunion: two patients remained unhealed in the first postoperative year. Finally, with the aid of nerve monitoring, we achieved more leg lengthening and less operating trauma without any neural complications, which verifies the value of intraoperative nerve monitoring in leg lengthening surgery.</p><p>Patients with previous hip surgery usually have malposition or adhesion of the nerves around the hip. Therefore, stretching and direct touching may injure the nerve. All three patients with previous hip surgery in the monitoring group had nerve alerts, which indicated that previous hip surgery might be a high-risk factor. According to the multivariate analysis of nerve injury in the control group, nerve injury had a strong relationship with the leg lengthening&#x2013;femur length ratio and previous hip surgery, rather than with leg-lengthening distance. From the multivariable analysis of nerve alerts in this study, previous hip surgery was the only risk factor. Leg lengthening could be controllable and less closely related to nerve injury under constant nerve monitoring.</p><p>We place our patients in 60&#x00B0; of hip flexion, internal rotation, and the maximal degree of knee flexion postoperatively to minimize the risk of nerve injury.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16">16</xref></sup> We suggest extending the hip and knee gradually to adapt the acute leg lengthening within three and four weeks.</p><p>This study has several limitations. First, the control group was retrospective, and the sample size was small, to the extent that it was not powered to detect the difference observed. Perhaps as a result of this, the difference in the primary outcome of nerve injury between the two groups did not reach statistical significance; however, there is an obvious trend towards reduced nerve injury with the aid of nerve monitoring. Second, the lack of randomization and blinding might lead to selection bias and recall bias. We are now planning to carry out a randomized controlled trial on this topic. Additionally, the surgeons possibly gained more awareness of nerve injury with increasing experience and took some extra precautions subconsciously, regardless of monitoring. Finally, the diagnosis of neural injury lacked an objective examination. While this might increase the risk of missing subtle nerve injuries, physical neurological examinations have demonstrated good reliability,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b42">42</xref></sup> and the standard of neurological examination was consistent in the two groups.</p><p>In conclusion, nerve injury usually occurred during the processes of exposure and reduction. The use of intraoperative nerve monitoring showed a trend towards reduced nerve injury in THA for Crowe IV DDH patients and allowed a greater restoration of leg length than was achieved in the control group. We recommend its routine use in patients undergoing leg lengthening, especially in those with previous hip surgery.</p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>During total hip arthroplasty (THA) for Crowe IV developmental dysplasia of the hip (DDH) patients, exposure and reduction were high-risk procedures in terms of nerve injury.</p></list-item><list-item><p><named-content specific-use="" xlink:title="" alt="">- </named-content>Intraoperative nerve monitoring might reduce nerve injury in THA for Crowe IV DDH patients.</p><p><named-content specific-use="" xlink:title="" alt="">- </named-content>Intraoperative123 nerve monitoring might reduce nerve injury in THA for Crowe IV DDH patients.</p></list-item></list><boxed-text id="B3"><label>Uncited Box 3.</label><caption><title>test-caption</title></caption><p>Test - Box Text</p><fn-group><fn fn-type="funding"><label>Funding</label><p>No benefits in any form have been received or will be received from a commercial party related directly or indirectly to the subject of this article.</p></fn><fn><p>Test - Box footnote</p></fn></fn-group></boxed-text><p><bold>Take home message</bold></p><p>- Paragraph text1.</p><p>- Paragraph text2.</p><p>- Paragraph text3.</p><p>- Paragraph text4.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="b1"><label>1. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Novais</surname> <given-names>EN</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Heare</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Kestel</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><x> </x><article-title>Multimodal nerve monitoring during periacetabular osteotomy identifies surgical steps associated with risk of injury</article-title><x>. </x><source>Int Orthop</source><x>. </x><year>2017</year><x>;</x><volume>41</volume><x>:</x><fpage>1543</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>1551</lpage><x>.</x><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00264-016-3394-x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b2"><label>2. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Yao</surname> <given-names>P-S</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Zheng</surname> <given-names>S-F</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Kang</surname> <given-names>D-Z</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Lin</surname> <given-names>Y-X</given-names></string-name></person-group><x>. </x><article-title>Surgery guided with intraoperative electrocorticography in patients with low-grade glioma and refractory seizures</article-title><x>. </x><source>J Neurosurg</source><x>. </x><year>2018</year><x>;</x><volume>128</volume><x>:</x><fpage>840</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>845</lpage><x>.</x><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3171/2016.11.JNS161296</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b3"><label>3. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Randolph</surname> <given-names>GW</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Kamani</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></string-name></person-group><x>. </x><article-title>Intraoperative neural monitoring in thyroid cancer surgery</article-title><x>. </x><source>Langenbecks Arch Surg</source><x>. </x><year>2014</year><x>;</x><volume>399</volume><x>:</x><fpage>199</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>207</lpage><x>.</x><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00423-013-1141-y</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b4"><label>4. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Park</surname> <given-names>J-H</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Hyun</surname> <given-names>S-J</given-names></string-name></person-group><x>. </x><article-title>Intraoperative neurophysiological monitoring in spinal surgery</article-title><x>. </x><source>World J Clin Cases</source><x>. </x><year>2015</year><x>;</x><volume>3</volume><x>:</x><fpage>765</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>773</lpage><x>.</x><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.12998/wjcc.v3.i9.765</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b5"><label>5. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Fehlings</surname> <given-names>MG</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Brodke</surname> <given-names>DS</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Norvell</surname> <given-names>DC</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Dettori</surname> <given-names>JR</given-names></string-name></person-group><x>. </x><article-title>The evidence for intraoperative neurophysiological monitoring in spine surgery: does it make a difference?</article-title><x> </x><source>Spine</source><x>. </x><year>2010</year><x>;</x><volume>35</volume><x>(</x><issue>9 Suppl</issue><x>):</x><fpage>S37</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>S46</lpage><x>.</x><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/BRS.0b013e3181d8338e</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b6"><label>6. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sutter</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Hersche</surname> <given-names>O</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Leunig</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><x> </x><article-title>Use of multimodal intra-operative monitoring in averting nerve injury during complex hip surgery</article-title><x>. </x><source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source><x>. </x><year>2012</year><x>;</x><volume>94-B</volume><x>:</x><fpage>179</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>184</lpage><x>.</x><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1302/0301-620X.94B2.28019</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b7"><label>7. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Sutherland</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Miller</surname> <given-names>DH</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Owen</surname> <given-names>JH</given-names></string-name></person-group><x>. </x><article-title>Use of spontaneous electromyography during revision and complex total hip arthroplasty</article-title><x>. </x><source>J Arthroplasty</source><x>. </x><year>1996</year><x>;</x><volume>11</volume><x>:</x><fpage>206</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>209</lpage><x>.</x><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0883-5403(05)80020-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b8"><label>8. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Satcher</surname> <given-names>RL</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Noss</surname> <given-names>RS</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Yingling</surname> <given-names>CD</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Ressler</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Ries</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name></person-group><x>. </x><article-title>The use of motor-evoked potentials to monitor sciatic nerve status during revision total hip arthroplasty</article-title><x>. </x><source>J Arthroplasty</source><x>. </x><year>2003</year><x>;</x><volume>18</volume><x>:</x><fpage>329</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>332</lpage><x>.</x><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1054/arth.2003.50055</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b9"><label>9. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Nercessian</surname> <given-names>OA</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Gonzalez</surname> <given-names>EG</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Stinchfield</surname> <given-names>FE</given-names></string-name></person-group><x>. </x><article-title>The use of somatosensory evoked potential during revision or reoperation for total hip arthroplasty</article-title><x>. </x><source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source><x>. </x><year>1989</year><x>;</x><volume>243</volume><x>:</x><fpage>138</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>142</lpage><x>.</x></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b10"><label>10. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kennedy</surname> <given-names>WF</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Byrne</surname> <given-names>TF</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Majid</surname> <given-names>HA</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Pavlak</surname> <given-names>LL</given-names></string-name></person-group><x>. </x><article-title>Sciatic nerve monitoring during revision total hip arthroplasty</article-title><x>. </x><source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source><x>. </x><year>1991</year><x>;</x><volume>264</volume><x>:</x><fpage>223</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>227</lpage><x>.</x></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b11"><label>11. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Brown</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>McGinnis</surname> <given-names>WC</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Mesghali</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group><x>. </x><article-title>Neurophysiologic intraoperative monitoring during revision total hip arthroplasty</article-title><x>. </x><source>J Bone Joint Surg [Am]</source><x>. </x><year>2002</year><x>;</x><volume>84</volume><x>(</x><issue>Suppl 2</issue><x>):</x><fpage>56</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>61</lpage><x>.</x><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2106/00004623-200200002-00007</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b12"><label>12. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Black</surname> <given-names>DL</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Reckling</surname> <given-names>FW</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Porter</surname> <given-names>SS</given-names></string-name></person-group><x>. </x><article-title>Somatosensory-evoked potential monitored during total hip arthroplasty</article-title><x>. </x><source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source><x>. </x><year>1991</year><x>;</x><volume>262</volume><x>:</x><fpage>170</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>177</lpage><x>.</x></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b13"><label>13. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Rasmussen</surname> <given-names>TJ</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Black</surname> <given-names>DL</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Bruce</surname> <given-names>RP</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Reckling</surname> <given-names>FW</given-names></string-name></person-group><x>. </x><article-title>Efficacy of corticosomatosensory evoked potential monitoring in predicting and/or preventing sciatic nerve palsy during total hip arthroplasty</article-title><x>. </x><source>J Arthroplasty</source><x>. </x><year>1994</year><x>;</x><volume>9</volume><x>:</x><fpage>53</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>61</lpage><x>.</x><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0883-5403(94)90137-6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b14"><label>14. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Porter</surname> <given-names>SS</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Black</surname> <given-names>DL</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Reckling</surname> <given-names>FW</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Mason</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name></person-group><x>. </x><article-title>Intraoperative cortical somatosensory evoked potentials for detection of sciatic neuropathy during total hip arthroplasty</article-title><x>. </x><source>J Clin Anesth</source><x>. </x><year>1989</year><x>;</x><volume>1</volume><x>:</x><fpage>170</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>176</lpage><x>.</x><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0952-8180(89)90037-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b15"><label>15. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Pereles</surname> <given-names>TR</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Stuchin</surname> <given-names>SA</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Kastenbaum</surname> <given-names>DM</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><x> </x><article-title>Surgical maneuvers placing the sciatic nerve at risk during total hip arthroplasty as assessed by somatosensory evoked potential monitoring</article-title><x>. </x><source>J Arthroplasty</source><x>. </x><year>1996</year><x>;</x><volume>11</volume><x>:</x><fpage>438</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>444</lpage><x>.</x><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0883-5403(96)80034-9</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b16"><label>16. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Shiramizu</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Naito</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Akiyoshi</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Yamaguchi</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></string-name></person-group><x>. </x><article-title>Acute effects of hip and knee positions on motor-evoked potentials of the sciatic nerve in total hip arthroplasty</article-title><x>. </x><source>Int Orthop</source><x>. </x><year>2003</year><x>;</x><volume>27</volume><x>:</x><fpage>211</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>213</lpage><x>.</x><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00264-003-0444-y</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b17"><label>17. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>K-H</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>H-Y</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Sung</surname> <given-names>C-S</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><x> </x><article-title>Wake-Up test in total hip arthroplasty with high-riding developmental dysplasia</article-title><x>. </x><source>Orthopedics</source><x>. </x><year>2014</year><x>;</x><volume>37</volume><x>:</x><fpage>e625</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>e630</lpage><x>.</x><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3928/01477447-20140626-53</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b18"><label>18. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Shemesh</surname> <given-names>SS</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Robinson</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Overley</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><x> </x><article-title>Novel technique for intraoperative sciatic nerve assessment in complex primary total hip arthroplasty: a pilot study</article-title><x>. </x><source>Hip Int</source><x>. </x><year>2018</year><x>;</x><volume>28</volume><x>:</x><fpage>210</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>217</lpage><x>.</x><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5301/hipint.5000553</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b19"><label>19. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Siebenrock</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>R&#x00F6;sler</surname> <given-names>KM</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Gonzalez</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Ganz</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name></person-group><x>. </x><article-title>Intraoperative electromyography of the superior gluteal nerve during lateral approach to the hip for arthroplasty</article-title><x>. </x><source>J Arthroplasty</source><x>. </x><year>2000</year><x>;</x><volume>15</volume><x>:</x><fpage>867</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>870</lpage><x>.</x><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1054/arth.2000.8099</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b20"><label>20. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Stone</surname> <given-names>RG</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Weeks</surname> <given-names>LE</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Hajdu</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Stinchfield</surname> <given-names>FE</given-names></string-name></person-group><x>. </x><article-title>Evaluation of sciatic nerve compromise during total hip arthroplasty</article-title><x>. </x><source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source><x>. </x><year>1985</year><x>;</x><volume>201</volume><x>:</x><fpage>26</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>31</lpage><x>.</x></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b21"><label>21. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Pring</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Trousdale</surname> <given-names>RT</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Cabanela</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Harper</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></string-name></person-group><x>. </x><article-title>Intraoperative electromyographic monitoring during Periacetabular osteotomy</article-title><x>. </x><source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source><x>. </x><year>2002</year><x>;</x><volume>400</volume><x>:</x><fpage>158</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>164</lpage><x>.</x><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00003086-200207000-00020</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b22"><label>22. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Porat</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Orozco</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Goyal</surname> <given-names>N</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Post</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Ong</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group><x>. </x><article-title>Neurophysiologic monitoring can predict iatrogenic injury during acetabular and pelvic fracture fixation</article-title><x>. </x><source>HSS J</source><x>. </x><year>2013</year><x>;</x><volume>9</volume><x>:</x><fpage>218</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>222</lpage><x>.</x><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11420-013-9347-7</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b23"><label>23. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Crowe</surname> <given-names>JF</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Mani</surname> <given-names>VJ</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Ranawat</surname> <given-names>CS</given-names></string-name></person-group><x>. </x><article-title>Total hip replacement in congenital dislocation and dysplasia of the hip</article-title><x>. </x><source>J Bone Joint Surg [Am]</source><x>. </x><year>1979</year><x>;</x><volume>61</volume><x>:</x><fpage>15</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>23</lpage><x>.</x><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2106/00004623-197961010-00004</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b24"><label>24. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lai</surname> <given-names>KA</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Lin</surname> <given-names>CJ</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Jou</surname> <given-names>IM</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Su</surname> <given-names>FC</given-names></string-name></person-group><x>. </x><article-title>Gait analysis after total hip arthroplasty with leg-length equalization in women with unilateral congenital complete dislocation of the hip--comparison with untreated patients</article-title><x>. </x><source>J Orthop Res</source><x>. </x><year>2001</year><x>;</x><volume>19</volume><x>:</x><fpage>1147</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>1152</lpage><x>.</x><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0736-0266(01)00032-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b25"><label>25. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Liu</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Fan</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><x> </x><article-title>Depression and anxiety before and after limb length discrepancy correction in patients with unilateral developmental dysplasia of the hip</article-title><x>. </x><source>J Psychosom Res</source><x>. </x><year>2015</year><x>;</x><volume>79</volume><x>:</x><fpage>574</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>579</lpage><x>.</x><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jpsychores.2015.08.002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b26"><label>26. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Rogers</surname> <given-names>BA</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Garbedian</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Kuchinad</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><x> </x><article-title>Total hip arthroplasty for adult hip dysplasia</article-title><x>. </x><source>The Journal of Bone &#x0026; Joint Surgery</source><x>. </x><year>2012</year><x>;</x><volume>94</volume><x>:</x><fpage>1809</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>1821</lpage><x>.</x><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2106/JBJS.K.00779</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b27"><label>27. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Regev</surname> <given-names>GJ</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Drexler</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Sever</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><x> </x><article-title>Neurolysis for the treatment of sciatic nerve palsy associated with total hip arthroplasty</article-title><x>. </x><source>Bone Joint J</source><x>. </x><year>2015</year><x>;</x><volume>97-B</volume><x>:</x><fpage>1345</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>1349</lpage><x>.</x><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1302/0301-620X.97B10.35590</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b28"><label>28. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Farrell</surname> <given-names>CM</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Springer</surname> <given-names>BD</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Haidukewych</surname> <given-names>GJ</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Morrey</surname> <given-names>BF</given-names></string-name></person-group><x>. </x><article-title>Motor nerve palsy following primary total hip arthroplasty</article-title><x>. </x><source>J Bone Joint Surg [Am]</source><x>. </x><year>2005</year><x>;</x><volume>87-A</volume><x>:</x><fpage>2619</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>2625</lpage><x>.</x></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b29"><label>29. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Edwards</surname> <given-names>BN</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Tullos</surname> <given-names>HS</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Noble</surname> <given-names>PC</given-names></string-name></person-group><x>. </x><article-title>Contributory factors and etiology of sciatic nerve palsy in total hip arthroplasty</article-title><x>. </x><source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source><x>. </x><year>1987</year><x>;</x><volume>218</volume><x>:</x><fpage>136</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>141</lpage><x>.</x></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b30"><label>30. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Nercessian</surname> <given-names>OA</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Piccoluga</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Eftekhar</surname> <given-names>NS</given-names></string-name></person-group><x>. </x><article-title>Postoperative sciatic and femoral nerve palsy with reference to leg lengthening and medialization/lateralization of the hip joint following total hip arthroplasty</article-title><x>. </x><source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source><x>. </x><year>1994</year><x>;</x><volume>304</volume><x>:</x><fpage>165</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>171</lpage><x>.</x></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b31"><label>31. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Eggli</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Hankemayer</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>M&#x00FC;ller</surname> <given-names>ME</given-names></string-name></person-group><x>. </x><article-title>Nerve palsy after leg lengthening in total replacement arthroplasty for developmental dysplasia of the hip</article-title><x>. </x><source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source><x>. </x><year>1999</year><x>;</x><volume>81-B</volume><x>:</x><fpage>843</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>845</lpage><x>.</x><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1302/0301-620X.81B5.0810843</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b32"><label>32. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Cooke</surname> <given-names>TD</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Scudamore</surname> <given-names>RA</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Bryant</surname> <given-names>JT</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><x> </x><article-title>A quantitative approach to radiography of the lower limb. principles and applications</article-title><x>. </x><source>J Bone Joint Surg [Br]</source><x>. </x><year>1991</year><x>;</x><volume>73-B</volume><x>:</x><fpage>715</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>720</lpage><x>.</x><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1302/0301-620X.73B5.1894656</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b33"><label>33. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Li</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>X</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Wang</surname> <given-names>Q</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><x> </x><article-title>Equalisation of leg lengths in total hip arthroplasty for patients with Crowe type-IV developmental dysplasia of the hip</article-title><x>. </x><source>Bone Joint J</source><x>. </x><year>2017</year><x>;</x><volume>99-B</volume><x>:</x><fpage>872</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>879</lpage><x>.</x><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1302/0301-620X.99B7.BJJ-2016-1328.R1</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b34"><label>34. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Massa</surname> <given-names>BSF</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Guarniero</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Godoy Jr</surname> <given-names>RM</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><x> </x><article-title>Use of inlet radiographs in the assessment of reduction after the surgical treatment of developmental dysplasia of the hip</article-title><x>. </x><source>Bone Joint J</source><x>. </x><year>2017</year><x>;</x><volume>99-B</volume><x>:</x><fpage>697</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>701</lpage><x>.</x><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1302/0301-620X.99B5.37687</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b35"><label>35. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>Z</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Luo</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Cheng</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Xiao</surname> <given-names>K</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Zhang</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group><x>. </x><article-title>Unexpected long lower limb in patients with unilateral hip dislocation</article-title><x>. </x><source>J Bone Joint Surg</source><x>. </x><year>2018</year><x>;</x><volume>100</volume><x>:</x><fpage>388</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>395</lpage><x>.</x><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2106/JBJS.17.00187</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b36"><label>36. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Paternostro-Sluga</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Grim-Stieger</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Posch</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><x> </x><article-title>Reliability and validity of the medical Research Council (MRC) scale and a modified scale for testing muscle strength in patients with radial palsy</article-title><x>. </x><source>J Rehabil Med</source><x>. </x><year>2008</year><x>;</x><volume>40</volume><x>:</x><fpage>665</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>671</lpage><x>.</x><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2340/16501977-0235</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b37"><label>37. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lai</surname> <given-names>K-A</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Shen</surname> <given-names>WJ</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Huang</surname> <given-names>L-W</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Chen</surname> <given-names>MY</given-names></string-name></person-group><x>. </x><article-title>Cementless total hip arthroplasty and limb-length equalization in patients with unilateral Crowe type-IV hip dislocation</article-title><x>. </x><source>J Bone Joint Surg [Am]</source><x>. </x><year>2005</year><x>;</x><volume>87-A</volume><x>:</x><fpage>339</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>345</lpage><x>.</x></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b38"><label>38. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Howie</surname> <given-names>CR</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Ohly</surname> <given-names>NE</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Miller</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></string-name></person-group><x>. </x><article-title>Cemented total hip arthroplasty with subtrochanteric osteotomy in dysplastic hips</article-title><x>. </x><source>Clin Orthop Relat Res</source><x>. </x><year>2010</year><x>;</x><volume>468</volume><x>:</x><fpage>3240</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>3247</lpage><x>.</x><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11999-010-1367-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b39"><label>39. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Eskelinen</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Helenius</surname> <given-names>I</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Remes</surname> <given-names>V</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><x> </x><article-title>Cementless total hip arthroplasty in patients with high congenital hip dislocation</article-title><x>. </x><source>J Bone Joint Surg [Am]</source><x>. </x><year>2006</year><x>;</x><volume>88-A</volume><x>:</x><fpage>80</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>91</lpage><x>.</x></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b40"><label>40. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Hasegawa</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Iwase</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Kanoh</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Seki</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Matsuoka</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></string-name></person-group><x>. </x><article-title>Total hip arthroplasty for Crowe type &#x2163; developmental dysplasia</article-title><x>. </x><source>J Arthroplasty</source><x>. </x><year>2012</year><x>;</x><volume>27</volume><x>:</x><fpage>1629</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>1635</lpage><x>.</x><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.arth.2012.02.026</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b41"><label>41. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Kabata</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Kajino</surname> <given-names>Y</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Inoue</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><x> </x><article-title>Safety range for acute limb lengthening in primary total hip arthroplasty</article-title><x>. </x><source>Int Orthop</source><x>. </x><year>2019</year><x>;</x><volume>43</volume><x>:</x><fpage>2047</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>2056</lpage><x>.</x><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00264-018-4158-6</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b42"><label>42. </label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Schmid</surname> <given-names>AB</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Brunner</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><string-name><surname>Luomajoki</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name><x>, </x><etal>et al.</etal></person-group><x> </x><article-title>Reliability of clinical tests to evaluate nerve function and mechanosensitivity of the upper limb peripheral nervous system</article-title><x>. </x><source>BMC Musculoskelet Disord</source><x>. </x><year>2009</year><x>;</x><volume>10</volume><x>:</x><elocation-id>11</elocation-id><x>.</x><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2474-10-11</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="b43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><comment>1</comment><person-group person-group-type="author"><string-name><surname>Lodewijkx</surname> <given-names>H</given-names></string-name></person-group><x>. </x><article-title>Individual-group continuity in cooperation and competition under varying communication conditions</article-title><x>. </x><source>Journal of Social Psychology</source><x>. </x><year>2001</year><x>;</x><volume>6</volume><x>(</x><issue>12</issue><x>):</x><fpage>166</fpage><x>&#x2013;</x><lpage>182</lpage><x>. </x><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.uiowa.edu/~grpproc/crisp/crisp.6.12.htm" xlink:type="simple">http://www.uiowa.edu/~grpproc/crisp/crisp.6.12.htm</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group content-type="bjj-author-contribs"><fn><p><bold>Author contributions</bold></p><p>X. Kong: Performed the experiments, Wrote the manuscript.</p><p>W. Chai: Performed the experiments, Wrote the manuscript.</p><p>J. Chen: Revised the manuscript, Helped perform the analysis with constructive discussions.</p><p>C. Yan: Revised the manuscript, Helped perform the analysis with constructive discussions.</p><p>L. Shi: Revised the manuscript, Helped perform the analysis with constructive discussions.</p><p>Y. Wang: Performed the surgery., Primarily responsible for oversight of the research project, Acquired and analyzed the data, Wrote the manuscript. X.&#x00A0;Kong and W. Chai contributed equally to this work.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="funding-group"><fn><p><bold>Funding statement</bold></p><p>No benefits in any form have been received or will be received from a commercial party related directly or indirectly to the subject of this article.</p><p><bold>Ethical review statement</bold></p><p>The study protocol was approved by the institutional review board of our hospital[JW1] . Informed consent was obtained from all the patients enrolled in the study.</p><p>This article was primary edited by A. D. Liddle.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>
