<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"><article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.2"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">elife</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eLife</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>eLife</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn publication-format="electronic" pub-type="epub">2050-084X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>eLife Sciences Publications, Ltd</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">64501</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.64501</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="display-channel"><subject>original article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Biochemistry</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="sub-display-channel"><subject>Meta-Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The growth of acronyms in the scientific literature</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" equal-contrib="yes" id="author-47050" deceased="yes"><name><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>Adrian</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-6339-0374</contrib-id><email>a.barnett@qut.edu.au</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="equal-contrib1">&#x2020;</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con1"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/><bio><p>Adrian Barnett is in the School of Public Health and Social Work, Queensland University of Technology, Brisbane, Australia</p></bio></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="author-195063"><name><surname>Tamil</surname><given-names>Selvan</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6768-4553</contrib-id><email>tamizhad@gmail.com</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf2"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes" id="author-195073"><name><surname>Doubleday</surname><given-names>Zoe</given-names></name><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0045-6377</contrib-id><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="fn" rid="equal-contrib1">&#x2020;</xref><xref ref-type="other" rid="fund2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="con2"/><xref ref-type="fn" rid="conf1"/><bio><p>Zoe Doubleday is in the Future Industries Institute, University of South Australia, Adelaide, Australia</p></bio></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label><institution content-type="dept">School of Public Health and Social Work, Queensland University of Technology</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Brisbane</named-content></addr-line><country>Australia</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label><institution content-type="dept">Future Industries Institute, University Of South Australia</institution><addr-line><named-content content-type="city">Mawson Lakes</named-content></addr-line><country>Australia</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Rodgers</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>eLife</institution><country>United Kingdom</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="senior_editor"><name><surname>Rodgers</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name><role>Senior Editor</role><aff><institution>eLife</institution><country>United Kingdom</country></aff></contrib><contrib contrib-type="senior_editor"><name><surname>Mickel</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><fn fn-type="con" id="equal-contrib1"><label>&#x2020;</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date publication-format="electronic" date-type="publication"><day>17</day><month>02</month><year>2021</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2021</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><elocation-id>e60080</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2020-06-16"><day>16</day><month>06</month><year>2020</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2020-07-14"><day>14</day><month>07</month><year>2020</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x00A9; 2020, Barnett et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2020</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Barnett et al</copyright-holder><ali:free_to_read/><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><ali:license_ref>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use and redistribution provided that the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="elife-64501.pdf"/><related-article related-article-type="companion" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.00012" id="ra1"/><related-article related-article-type="companion" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.18990" id="ra2"/><related-article related-article-type="companion" ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7554/eLife.20054" id="ra3"/><abstract><p>Abstract: Some acronyms are useful and are widely understood, but many of the acronyms used in scientific papers hinder understanding and contribute to the increasing fragmentation of science. Here we report the results of an analysis of more than 24 million article titles and 18 million article abstracts published between 1950 and 2019. There was at least one acronym in 19% of the titles and 73% of the abstracts. Acronym use has also increased over time, but the re-use of acronyms has declined. We found that from more than one million unique acronyms in our data, just over 2000 (0.2%) were used regularly, and most acronyms (79%) appeared fewer than 10 times. Acronyms are not the biggest current problem in science communication, but reducing their use is a simple change that would help readers and potentially increase the value of science.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-keywords"><kwd>meta-research</kwd><kwd>scientific writing</kwd><kwd>acronyms</kwd><kwd>communication</kwd><kwd>knowledge</kwd><kwd>scientific publishing</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="research-organism"><title>Research organism</title><kwd>None</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group id="fund1"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100000925</institution-id><institution>National Health and Medical Research Council</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>APP1117784</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>Adrian</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><award-group id="fund2"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100000923</institution-id><institution>Australian Research Council</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>FT190100244</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Doubleday</surname><given-names>Zoe</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group><funding-statement>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication.</funding-statement></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta specific-use="meta-only"><meta-name>Author impact statement</meta-name><meta-value>A study of 24 million articles has revealed that scientists have created more than 1 million acronyms since 1950, most of which have been used fewer than 10 times.</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1" sec-type="intro"><title>Introduction</title><p>As the number of scientific papers published every year continues to grow, individual papers are also becoming increasingly specialised and complex (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib5">Delanty, 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1">Bornmann and Mutz, 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Doubleday and Connell, 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4">Cordero et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20">Plav&#x00E9;n-Sigray et al., 2017</xref>). This information overload is driving a "knowledge-ignorance paradox" whereby informationChemical structure 1 increases but knowledge that can be put to good use does not (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Jeschke et al., 2019</xref>). Writing scientific papers that are clearer to read could help to close this gap and increase the usefulness of scientific research (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8">Freeling et al., 2019</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14">Letchford et al., 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11">Heard, 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib9">Glasziou et al., 2014</xref>).</p><fig id="C1" position="anchor"><label>Chemical structure 1.</label><caption><title>sample CS caption</title></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-64501-chem1.tif"/></fig><p>One feature that can make scientific papers difficult to read is the widespread use of acronyms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Sword, 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19">Pinker, 2015</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10">Hales et al., 2017</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15">Lowe, 2019</xref>), and many researchers have given examples of the overuse of acronyms, and highlighted the ambiguities, misunderstandings and inefficiencies they cause (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7">Fred and Cheng, 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16">Narod et al., 2016</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18">Patel and Rashid, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Potteg&#x00E5;rd et al., 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25">Weale et al., 2018</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17">Parvaiz et al., 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib3">Chang et al., 2002</xref>). For example, the acronym UA has 18 different meanings in medicine (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Lang, 2019</xref>). contains four sentences from published papers that show how acronyms can hinder understanding.</p><boxed-text id="box1"><title id="B1">Examples of sentences with multiple acronyms.</title><p>The four sentences below are taken from abstracts published since 2000, and reflect the increasing complexity and specialisation of science.</p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>"Applying PROBAST showed that ADO, B-AE-D, B-AE-D-C, extended ADO, updated ADO, updated BODE, and a model developed by Bertens et al were derived in studies assessed as being at low risk of bias." (2019)</p></list-item><list-item><p>"Toward this goal, the CNNT, the CRN, and the CNSW will each propose programs to the NKF for improving the knowledge and skills of the professionals within these councils." (2000)</p></list-item><list-item><p>"After their co-culture with HC-MVECs, SSc BM-MSCs underwent to a phenotypic modulation which re-programs these cells toward a pro-angiogenic behaviour." (2013)</p></list-item><list-item><p>"RUN had significantly (<italic>P</italic>&#x003C;0.05) greater size-adjusted CSMI and BSI than C, SWIM, and CYC; and higher size, age, and YST-adjusted CSMI and BSI than SWIM and CYC." (2002)</p></list-item></list></boxed-text><p>In this article we report trends in the use of acronyms in the scientific literature from 1950 to the present. We examined acronyms because they can be objectively identified and reflect changes in specialisation and clarity in writing.</p></sec><sec id="s2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><p>We analysed 24,873,372 titles and 18,249,091 abstracts published between 1950 and 2019, which yielded 1,112,345 unique acronyms. We defined an acronym as a word in which half or more of the characters are upper case letters. For example, mRNA and BRCA1 (Chemical structure 2)are both acronyms according to this definition, but N95 is not because two of the three characters are not upper case letters.</p><fig id="C2" position="anchor"><label>Chemical structure 2.</label><caption><title>sample CS caption</title></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-64501-chem2.tif"/></fig><disp-quote><p>We found that the proportion of acronyms in titles increased from 0.7 per 100 words in 1950&#x2013;2.4 per 100 words in 2019; the proportion of acronyms in abstracts also increased, from 0.4 per 100 words in 1956&#x2013;4.1 per 100 words in 2019. There was at least one acronym in 19% of titles and 73% of abstracts. Three letter acronyms (jokingly called TLAs) were also more popular than acronyms of two and four letters.</p></disp-quote><p>The proportion of acronyms in titles has flattened since around the year 2000, whereas the proportion in abstracts continued to increase. Moreover, when the 100 most popular acronyms were removed, there was still a clear increase in acronym use over time. Furthermore, the increase was visible in all the article types we studied (including articles, clinical trials, case reports, comments and editorials: ). shows the top ten acronyms in titles for every year from 1950&#x2013;2019,, and shows the top ten acronyms in abstracts over the same period.</p><p>There are 17,576 possible three-letter acronyms using the upper case letters of the alphabet. We found that 94% of these combinations had been used at least once. Strikingly, out of the 1.1 million acronyms analysed, we found that the majority were rarely used, with 30% occurring only once, and 49% occurring between two and ten time times. Only 0.2% of acronyms (just over 2,000) occurred more than 10,000 times. One year after their first use, only 11% of acronyms had been re-used in a different paper in the same journal. Longer acronyms were less likely to be re-used, with a 17% re-use for two-character acronyms, compared with just 8% for acronyms of five characters or longer. The time taken for acronyms to be re-used has also increased over time (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig1">Figure 1</xref>), indicating that acronyms created today are less likely to be re-used than previously created acronyms.</p><fig id="fig2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>.Estimated time to re-use of acronyms over time.</title></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-64501-fig2.tif"/></fig><p>DNA is by far the most common acronym and is universally recognised by scientists and the public (1). However, not all the top 20 may be so widely recognised, and it is an interesting individual exercise to test whether you, the reader, recognise them all. Six of the top 20 acronyms also have multiple common meanings in the health and medical literature, such as US and HR&#x201A; although the meaning can usually be inferred from the sentence.</p><p>In parallel with increasing acronym use, the average number of words in titles and abstracts has increased over time, with a steady and predominantly linear increase for titles, and a more nonlinear increase for abstracts. The average title length increased from 9.0 words in 1950&#x2013;14.6 words in 2019, and shows no sign of flattening. The average abstract length has also increased, from 128 words in 1962&#x2013;220 words in 2019, and again this trend shows no sign of flattening. It is worth pointing out that these increases have happened despite the word and character limits that many journals place on the length of titles and abstracts.</p><table-wrap id="keyresource" position="anchor"><label>Uncited Table 1.</label><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="top">MArks</th><th align="left" valign="top">Sub</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="top">45</td><td align="left" valign="top">M</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">55</td><td align="left" valign="top">E</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">60</td><td align="left" valign="top">T</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="top">57</td><td align="left" valign="top">S</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Our results show a clear increase over time in the use of acronyms titles and abstracts, with most acronyms being used less than 10 times. Titles a<inline-graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="jpeg" xlink:href="/resources/elife/elife/eLife.64501/resources/0ebe9354-22bf-4238-98f4-1d8fc898005f.png.JPEG"/>nd abstracts are also getting longer, meaning readers are now required to read more content of greater complexity.</p><p>There have been many calls to reduce the use of acronyms and jargon in scientific papers (see, for example, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24">Talk Medicine, 2019</xref>, which recommends a maximum of three acronyms per paper), and many journal and academic writing guides recommend a sparing use of acronyms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23">Sword, 2012</xref>). However, the trends we report suggest that many scientists either ignore these guidelines or simply emulate what has come before. Entrenched writing styles in science are difficult to shift (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6">Doubleday and Connell, 2017</xref>), and the creation of new acronyms has become an acceptable part of scientific practice, and for clinical trials is a recognised form of branding (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib21">Potteg&#x00E5;rd et al., 2014</xref>).</p><p>We believe that scientists should use fewer acronyms when writing scientific papers. In particular, they should avoid using acronyms that might save a small amount of ink but do not save any syllables, such as writing HR instead of heart rate (Pinker, 2105; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13">Lang, 2019</xref>). This approach might also make articles easier to read and understand, and even help avoid potential confusion (as HR can also mean hazard ratio or hour). For more complex phrases with multiple syllables and specialist words, such as methylcyclopentadienyl manganese tricarbonyl (MMT), acronyms may ease reading and aid understanding, although MMT might mean methadone maintenance treatment to some readers.</p><p>It is difficult to make a general rule about which acronyms to keep and which to spell out. However, there is scope for journals to reduce the use of acronyms by, for example, only permitting the use of certain established acronyms (although the list of allowed acronyms would have to vary from journal to journal). In the future it might be possible, software permitting, for journals to offer two versions of the same paper, one with acronyms and without, so that the reader can select the version they prefer.</p><p>Our work shows that new acronyms are too common, and common acronyms are too rare. Reducing acronyms should boost understanding and reduce the gap between the information we produce and the knowledge that we use (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12">Jeschke et al., 2019</xref>) &#x201A; without 'dumbing down' the science. We suggest a second use for DNA: do not abbreviate.</p></sec><sec id="s4" sec-type="methods|materials"><title>Methods and materials</title><p>We use the word acronym to refer to acronyms (such as AIDS), initialisms (such as WHO) and abbreviations that include capital letters (such as BRCA). We use this broad definition because we were interested in shortened words that a reader is either expected to know or could potentially misunderstand. We did not define acronyms as those defined by the authors using parentheses, because many acronyms were not defined.</p><p>We defined an acronym as a word in which half or more of the characters are upper case letters. For example, mRNA is an acronym because it has three upper case letters out of four characters. Characters include numbers, so BRCA1 is also an acronym according to our definition, but N95 is not because two of the three characters are not upper case letters. (It shouldChemical structure 3, however, be noted that N95 is an abbreviation for National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health mask that filters at least 95% of airborne particles). Our definition of an acronym was arrived at using trial and error based on the number of acronyms captured and missed.</p><fig id="C3" position="anchor"><label>Chemical structure 3.</label><caption><title>sample CS caption</title></caption><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-64501-chem3.tif"/></fig><p>We included common acronyms (such as AIDS) because it is difficult to make a simple ruling about what is common and hence well accepted. We instead used(Chemical structure 3) a sensitivity analysis that excluded the most common acronyms. We did not include acronyms that have become common words and are generally now not written in upper case letters (such as laser).</p><sec id="s4-1"><title>Data extraction</title><p>The data were extracted from the PubMed repository of health and medical journals provided by the National Library of Medicine. Data were downloaded between 14 and 22 April 2020. Although the PubMed repository includes papers going back to the year 1781, we used 1950 as the first year. This is because although acronyms have been around for 5,000 years, their use greatly increased after the Second World War (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2">Cannon, 1989</xref>) and there were a relatively small number of papers in PubMed prior to 1950. The details of the algorithm to extract acronyms are in Appendix 1.</p></sec><sec id="s4-2"><title>Random checks of the algorithm</title><p>One researcher (AB) randomly checked 300 of each of the following by hand to verify our acronym-finding algorithm:</p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Titles that were excluded</p></list-item><list-item><p>Titles defined as having no acronyms</p></list-item><list-item><p>Titles defined as having at least one acronym</p></list-item><list-item><p>Abstracts defined as having no acronyms</p></list-item><list-item><p>Abstracts defined as having at least one acronym</p></list-item></list><p>The numbers in 2 are the count of errors and estimated upper bound for the error percentage using a Bayesian calculation based on the 95th percentile of a beta distribution using the observed number of papers with and without errors. The average error rates were between 0.3% and 6.3%. Zero error rates are unlikely given the great variety of styles across journals and authors. Examples of acronyms missed by our algorithm include those with a relatively large number of lower case letters, numbers, symbols or punctuation (such as circRNA). Examples of acronyms wrongly included by our algorithm include words written in capitals for emphasis and the initials of someone's name appearing in the title as part of a Festschrift.</p></sec><sec id="s4-3"><title>Exclusion reasons and numbers</title><p><label>3</label>lists the most common reasons why papers were excluded from our analysis. Papers were excluded if they were not written in English, and this was the main exclusion reason for titles. Over 7&#x00A0;million papers had no abstract and around 10,000 had an abstract that was empty or just one word long. Over 298,000 titles and 112,000 abstracts had 60% or more of words in capital letters, making it difficult to distinguish acronyms. This 60% threshold for exclusion was found using trial and error.</p></sec><sec id="s4-4"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>We examined trends over time by plotting annual averages. The trends were the average number of words in the title and abstract, and the proportion of acronyms in abstracts and titles using word count as the denominator. To examine varied types of acronyms, we split the trends according to acronyms that were letters only compared with those using letters and numbers. We also examined trends according to the length of the acronym. We calculated 95% confidence intervals for the annual means, but in general these were very close to the mean because of the enormous sample size, and hence we do not present them.</p><p>We examined the re-use of acronyms after their first use by calculating the number of acronyms re-used in a different paper in the same journal up to one year after their first use. We used the same journal in an attempt to standardise by field and so reduce the probability of counting re-uses for different meanings (such as ED meaning emergency department in the field of emergency medicine and eating disorder in the field of psychology). We counted re-use in the title or abstract. We censored times according to the last issue of the journal. We examined whether re-use was associated with the length of the acronym.</p><p>All data management and analyses were made using R version 3.6.1 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22">R Core Team, 2020</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s4-5"><title>Data and code availability</title><p>The analysis code and data to replicate all parts of the analyses and generate the figures and tables are available from GitHub: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/agbarnett/acronyms.">https://github.com/agbarnett/acronyms.</ext-link> We welcome re-use and the repository is licensed under the terms of the MIT license.</p></sec><sec id="s4-6"><title>Limitations</title><p>Our algorithm missed a relatively large number of acronyms that included symbols, punctuation and lower case letters. This means our estimates likely underestimate the total number of acronyms. We assumed this error is balanced over time, meaning our trends reflect a real increase in acronym use. We only examined abstracts and titles, not the main text. This is because we used an automated procedure to extract the data, and large numbers of main texts are only available for open access journals and only for recent years, making these data unsuitable for examining broad trends across the scientific literature. We took a broad look at overall trends and did not examine trends within journals or fields. However, our code and data are freely available, and hence other trends and patterns could be examined.</p><p>Acronyms are generally less common in titles than abstracts, and the proportion in titles has been relatively stable since 2000, but there was an increase from 1960&#x2013;2000 (bottom left and right). Three-character acronyms (blue lines) are more common than two-character acronyms (brown-orange lines) and four-character acronyms (olive green lines) in both titles and abstracts. A sufficient number of abstracts only became available from 1956. The spikes in titles for acronyms of length 2+ in 1952 and 1964 are because of the relatively small number of papers in those years, with over 78,000 papers being excluded in 1964 because the title was in capitals. (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp1">Supplementary file 1</xref>)</p><p>Each line shows the trend after excluding up to the <italic>n</italic> most popular acronyms (n=1, ..., 100). The darkest line is for n=1, and the lightest line is for n=100. The number of titles and journals in the early 1950s is much smaller, hence the more erratic trend for titles in that decade.</p><p>Data for six article types (journal article, clinical trial, case report, comment, editorial, and other). The high proportion of acronyms in the 1950s and 1960s for "other" is driven by a relatively large number of obituaries that include qualifications, such as FRCP (Fellow of the Royal College of Physicians) or DSO (Distinguished Service Order). The drop in the proportion of acronyms in 2019 for "clinical trials" and "other" may be due to a delay in papers from some journals appearing in PubMed.</p><p>Using a truncated y&#x2212;axis more clearly shows the upward trend in the use of acronyms in titles for all article types over time (by reducing the influence of "other" in the 1950s and 1960s; see Figure 1&#x2014;figure supplement 2).</p><p>The solid line is the estimated time in years for 10% of newly coined acronyms to be re-used in the same journal. 10% was chosen based on the overall percentage of acronyms being re-used within a year. Newly coined acronyms are grouped by year. The dotted lines show the 95% confidence interval for the time to re-use, which narrows over time as the sample size increases. The general trend is of an increasing time to re-use from 1965 onwards, which indicates that acronyms are being re-used less often. The relatively slow times to re-use in the 1950s and early 1960s are likely due to the very different mix of journals in that time.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Note</title><p>This Feature Article is part of a collection onmental health in academia.</p><table-wrap id="table1" position="float"><label>Uncited Table 1.</label><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom">MArks</th><th align="left" valign="bottom">Sub</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">45</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">M</td></tr><tr><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">55</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">E</td></tr><tr><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">60</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">T</td></tr><tr><td align="char" char="." valign="bottom">57</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">S</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><boxed-text id="box2"><label>Uncited Box 2.</label><caption><title>hhhhhhh</title></caption><p>hh</p><fn-group><fn><p>hhh</p></fn></fn-group></boxed-text></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="additional-information" id="s6"><title>Additional information</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interest"><title>Competing interests</title><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf1"><p>No competing interests declared</p></fn><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="conf2"><p>Senior Editor</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><fn fn-type="con" id="con1"><p>Conceptualization, Formal analysis, Software, Validation, Visualization, Writing &#x2013; original draft</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="con2"><p>Conceptualization, Investigation, Writing &#x2013; original draft</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="ethics-information"><title>Ethics</title><fn fn-type="other"><p>All work was done under theapproval of the Weill Cornell Medicine InstitutionalReview Board (IRB# 1612017849), and all respondentsprovided consent for participation in the study.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s7"><title>Additional files</title><supplementary-material id="supp1"><label>Supplementary file 1.</label><media xlink:href="/resources/elife/elife/eLife.64501/resources/6daf2efc-f7a4-40c6-a72d-92a773c64902.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="docx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="transrepform"><label>Transparent reporting form</label><media xlink:href="/resources/elife/elife/eLife.64501/resources/4c034b3e-a6b1-40e1-b65e-50d517645b8d.docx" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="docx"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material id="scode1"><label>Source code 1.</label><media xlink:href="/resources/elife/elife/eLife.64501/resources/af180c79-3dbb-4681-bade-bef033899053.png" mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png"/></supplementary-material></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s8"><title>Data availability</title><p>The analysis code and data to replicate all parts of the analyses and generate the figures and tables are available from GitHub: https://github.com/agbarnett/acronyms. We welcome re-use and the repository is licensed under the terms of the MIT license.</p><disp-quote><p>The following dataset was generated:</p></disp-quote><p><element-citation publication-type="data" specific-use="isSupplementedBy" id="dataset1">National Library of Medicine<year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><data-title>Figshare</data-title><source>figshare</source><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">8855795</pub-id>figshare</element-citation></p><p>The following previously published datasets were used:</p><p><element-citation publication-type="data" specific-use="references" id="dataset2"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barnett</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Doubleday</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><source>Docker Hub</source><comment>2019-08-30</comment><pub-id pub-id-type="other">2019-08-30</pub-id>other</element-citation></p></sec><ack id="ack"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>Computational resources and services were provided by the eResearch Office at Queensland University of Technology. We thank Ruth Tulleners for help with searching the literature and checking the data, and Angela Dean for comments on a draft.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bib1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bornmann</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mutz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>Growth rates of modern science: a bibliometric analysis based on the number of publications and cited references</article-title><source>J Assoc Inform Sci Tech</source><volume>66</volume><fpage>2215</fpage><lpage>2222</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cannon</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1989">1989</year><article-title>Abbreviations and acronyms in English word-formation</article-title><source>American Speech</source><volume>64</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>127</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chang</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name><name><surname>Sch&#x00FC;tze</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2002">2002</year><article-title>Creating an online dictionary of abbreviations from Medline</article-title><source>JournaloftheAmericanMedical Informatics Association : JAMIA</source><volume>9</volume><fpage>612</fpage><lpage>620</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1197/jamia.m1139</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12386112</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cordero</surname><given-names>RJB</given-names></name><name><surname>de Le&#x00F3;n-Rodriguez</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Alvarado-Torres</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><name><surname>Casadevall</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Life science's average publishable unit (apu) has increased over the past two decades</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>e0156983</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0156983</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27310929</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Delanty</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="1998">1998</year><article-title>The idea of the University in the global era: from knowledge as an end to the end of knowledge?</article-title><source>Soc Epistemol</source><volume>12</volume><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>25</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Doubleday</surname><given-names>ZA</given-names></name><name><surname>Connell</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Publishing with objective charisma: breaking science's paradox</article-title><source>Trends in ecology &#x0026; evolution</source><volume>32</volume><fpage>803</fpage><lpage>805</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tree.2017.06.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28734592</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fred</surname><given-names>HL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>TO</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2003">2003</year><article-title>Acronymesis: the exploding misuse of acronyms</article-title><source>Texas Heart Institute journal</source><volume>30</volume><fpage>255</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14677733</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Freeling</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Doubleday</surname><given-names>ZA</given-names></name><name><surname>Connell</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Opinion: how can we boost the impact of publications? try better writing</article-title><source>PNAS</source><volume>116</volume><fpage>341</fpage><lpage>343</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1819937116</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30622212</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Glasziou</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Altman</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bossuyt</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Boutron</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Julious</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Michie</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Moher</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Wager</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Reducing waste from incomplete or unusable reports of biomedical research</article-title><source>The Lancet</source><volume>383</volume><fpage>267</fpage><lpage>276</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><element-citation publication-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hales</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Rector</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>Alienating the audience: how abbreviations hamper scientific communication</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.psychologicalscience.org/observer/alienating-the-audience-how-abbreviations-hamper-scientific-communication%20[Accessed:%209%20July%202020]">https://www.psychologicalscience.org/observer/alienating-the-audience-how-abbreviations-hamper-scientific-communication [Accessed: 9 July 2020]</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heard</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>On whimsy, jokes, and beauty: can scientific writing be enjoyed?</article-title><source>Ideas Ecol Evol</source><volume>7</volume><fpage>64</fpage><lpage>72</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jeschke</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Lokatis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartram</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Tockner</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Knowledge in the dark: scientific challenges and ways forward</article-title><source>FACETS</source><volume>4</volume><fpage>423</fpage><lpage>441</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>The long and the short of abbreviations</article-title><source>European Science Editing</source><volume>45</volume><fpage>1114</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Letchford</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Moat</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Preis</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><article-title>The advantage of short paper titles</article-title><source>Royal Society open science</source><volume>2</volume><elocation-id>15026</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsos.150266</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26361556</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><element-citation publication-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Acronym fever: we need an Acronym for that</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://blogs.sciencemag.org/pipeline/archives/2019/07/18/acronym-fever-we-need-an-acronym-for-that%20[Accessed:%209%20July%202020]">https://blogs.sciencemag.org/pipeline/archives/2019/07/18/acronym-fever-we-need-an-acronym-for-that [Accessed: 9 July 2020]</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Narod</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ahmed</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Akbari</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2016">2016</year><article-title>Do acronyms belong in the medical literature?</article-title><source>Curr Oncol</source><volume>23</volume><fpage>295</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parvaiz</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Singh</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hafeez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Sharma</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2006">2006</year><article-title>Do multidisciplinary team members correctly interpret the abbreviations used in the medical records?</article-title><source>Scottish Medical Journal</source><volume>51</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>6</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name><name><surname>Rashid</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2009">2009</year><article-title>Averting the proliferation of acronymophilia in dermatology: effectively avoiding ADCOMSUBORDCOMPHIBSPAC</article-title><source>JournaloftheAmerican Academy of Dermatology</source><volume>60</volume><fpage>340</fpage><lpage>344</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaad.2008.10.035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19150279</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pinker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2015">2015</year><source>The Sense of Style: The Thinking Person's Guide to Writing in the 21st Century</source><publisher-name>Penguin Books</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plav&#x00E9;n-Sigray</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Matheson</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Schiffler</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2017">2017</year><article-title>The readability of scientific texts is decreasing over time</article-title><source>eLife</source><volume>6</volume><elocation-id>e27725</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.27725</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28873054</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Potteg&#x00E5;rd</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Haastrup</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Stage</surname><given-names>TB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Meegaard</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Meegaard</surname><given-names>LHV</given-names></name><name><surname>Horneberg</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Gils</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dideriksen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Aagaard</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Almarsdottir</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Hallas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Damkier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year><article-title>Search for humourIstic and Extravagant acroNyms and Thoroughly inappropriate names for important clinical trials (scientific): qualitative and quantitative systematic study</article-title><source>BMJ</source><volume>349</volume><elocation-id>g7092</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.g7092</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25516539</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><element-citation publication-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>R Core Team</collab></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2020">2020</year><article-title>The R project for statistical computing</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.R-project.org/%20[Accessed:%209%20July%202020]">https://www.R-project.org/ [Accessed: 9 July 2020]</ext-link></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sword</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2012">2012</year><source>Stylish Academic Writing</source><publisher-name>Harvard University Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><element-citation publication-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Talk Medicine</surname><given-names>BMJ</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2019">2019</year><article-title>Podcast: Talk Evidence &#x2013; aggravating acronyms and screening (again). Available at:</article-title><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://soundcloud.com/bmjpodcasts/talk-evidence-november-2019-acronyms-timing-of-dose-and-screening">https://soundcloud.com/bmjpodcasts/talk-evidence-november-2019-acronyms-timing-of-dose-and-screening</ext-link><date-in-citation iso-8601-date="July 2020-Accessed:-Accessed:">9 Accessed:, July 2020</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weale</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Soysa</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Yentis</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><year iso-8601-date="2018">2018</year><article-title>Use of acronyms in anaesthetic and associated investigations: appropriate or unnecessary? - the UOAIAAAIAOU Study</article-title><source>Anaesthesia</source><volume>73</volume><fpage>1531</fpage><lpage>1534</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/anae.14450</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30412290</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><app-group><app id="appendix-"><title>Appendix </title></app><app id="appendix-"><title>Appendix </title><sec sec-type="appendix" id="s9"><title>Text processing algorithm</title><p>The data were downloaded in eXtensible Markup Language (XML) format and read into R for processing. The complete R code is freely available on GitHub. The list of key processing steps in order are below. Unless otherwise stated, each step was applied to the title and abstract.</p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Read the data into R using UTF-8 encoding.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Remove commonly used copyright sentences such as "This article is protected by copyright" from the abstract.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Extract the PubMed ID, date the paper was added to PubMed, title, abstract, journal name, article type, language, and number of authors.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Remove copyright sections and sub-headings from the abstract (such as "BACKGROUND").</p></list-item><list-item><p>Remove systematic review registrations from the abstract.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Exclude papers not in English.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Exclude titles and abstracts that are empty.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Exclude abstracts of 10 words or fewer that have the article type Published Erratum because they are usually just a citation/note.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Remove Roman numerals from 1 to 30 (that is, from I to XXX). The upper limit of 30 was based on trial and error. Also remove Roman numerals suffixed with a lower case letter or "th".</p></list-item><list-item><p>Remove the chromosomes: XX, XY, XO, ZO, XXYY, ZW, ZWW, XXX, XXXX, XXXXX, YYYYY.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Remove symbols, including mathematical symbols, spacing symbols, punctuation, currencies, trademarks, arrows, superscripts and subscripts.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Remove common capitals from the title (such as WITHDRAWN, CORRIGENDUM and EDITORIAL).</p></list-item><list-item><p>Remove sub-headings (such as SETTING and SUBJECTS) from the abstract. (This step is performed in addition to the sub-heading removal step mentioned above).</p></list-item><list-item><p>Replace common units in the abstract with "dummy" (for example, change &#x201C;kg/m2&#x201D; to &#x201C;dummy&#x201D;) so that they are counted as one word during word counts.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Remove full-stops in acronyms (so that, for example, W.H.O. becomes WHO).</p></list-item><list-item><p>Replace all plurals by replacing "s " with a space. This removes plurals from acronyms: for example, EDs becomes ED.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Break the title and abstract into words.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Exclude the title or abstract if 60% or more of the words are in capitals as this is a journal style and makes it hard to find acronyms.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Exclude abstracts with strings of four or more words in capitals. Trial and error showed that this was a journal style and it makes it hard to spot acronyms.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Exclude the title if the first four words or last four words are in capitals. This is a journal style.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Remove gene sequences defined as characters of six or more than only contain the letters A, T, C, G, U and p.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Find and exclude citations to the current paper in the abstract, as these often have author initials which look like acronyms.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Exclude titles of just one word.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Exclude papers with a missing PubMed Date.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Extract acronyms, defined as a word where half or more of the characters are upper case.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Exclude acronyms longer than 15 characters, as these are often gene strings.</p></list-item></list><p>We did not include the following as acronyms:</p><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>Common units of measurement like pH&#x201A; hr or mL.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Chemical symbols like Na or Ca.</p></list-item><list-item><p>Acronyms that have become common words (such as laser).</p></list-item><list-item><p>e.g. and i.e.</p></list-item></list><p>Table 3 Reasons for excluding titles and abstracts, along with the numbers excluded for each reason</p><p>Reason Titles Abstract</p><p>No abstract n/a 7,253,053</p><p>Non-English 4,783,569 4,783,569</p><p>Pre-1950 384,436 7,973</p><p>Title/abstract largely in capitals 298,284 112,369</p><p>One word title/abstract 76,303 201</p><p>Empty title/abstract 149 9,887</p><p>Missing PubMed date 1,510 1,510</p><p>Duplicate PubMed ID 1,344 1,328<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="table1scode1">Table 1&#x2014;source code 1</xref></p><p>No article type 109 0</p></sec></app><app id="appendix-"><title>Appendix </title></app></app-group></back><sub-article article-type="decision-letter" id="sa1"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.64501.sa1</article-id><title-group><article-title>Decision letter</article-title></title-group><contrib-group content-type="section"><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Rodgers</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name><role>Reviewing Editor</role><aff><institution>eLife</institution><country>United Kingdom</country></aff></contrib></contrib-group></front-stub><boxed-text><p>In the interests of transparency, eLife publishes the most substantive revision requests and the accompanying author responses.</p></boxed-text><p><bold>Acceptance summary:</bold></p><p>This paper presents exciting evidence that the bHLH transcription factor Olig3 controls the development of both cerebellar germinal zones. The data therefore have major implications for how GABAergic and glutamatergic neurons are produced.</p><p><bold>Decision letter after peer review:</bold></p><p>Thank you for submitting your article "Olig3 acts as a master regulator of cerebellar development" for consideration by <italic>eLife</italic>. Your article has been reviewed by three peer reviewers, and the evaluation has been overseen by a Reviewing Editor and Marianne Bronner as the Senior Editor. The following individuals involved in review of your submission have agreed to reveal their identity: Victor V Chizhikov (Reviewer #1); David J Solecki (Reviewer #2); Kimberly A Aldinger (Reviewer #3).</p><p>The reviewers have discussed the reviews with one another and the Reviewing Editor has drafted this decision to help you prepare a revised submission.</p><p>We would like to draw your attention to changes in our revision policy that we have made in response to COVID-19 (https://elifesciences.org/articles/57162). Specifically, we are asking editors to accept without delay manuscripts, like yours, that they judge can stand as <italic>eLife</italic> papers without additional data, even if they feel that they would make the manuscript stronger. Thus the revisions requested below only address clarity and presentation.</p><p>Summary:</p><p>This work identifies the bHLH transcription factor Olig3 as a protein expressed in the germinal zones of the developing mouse cerebellum. The authors used a combination of histology as well as quantification of immunohistochemistry data, fate mapping, and in utero electroporation in control and mutant mice to test the role of Olig3 during cerebellar development. The data demonstrate key functions for Olig3+ in cells of the rhombic lip and ventricular zone, the two progenitor zones that give rise to cerebellar glutamatergic and GABAergic neurons, respectively.</p><p>Essential revisions:</p><p>The reviewers have made suggestions on how to improve the clarity of specific figures. Please see below for details. In addition, there are a number of suggestions to improve the clarity of how the data are interpreted. Therefore, there are minor additional data analysis/experiments required and several instances of reworking the text.</p><p>Title:</p><p>Please consider revising the title. The use of "master regulator" in particular could be toned down. Perhaps "early" regulator may be more appropriate.</p><p><italic>Reviewer #1:</italic></p><p>Lowenstein et al., describe the novel roles of Olig3 in cerebellar development. The authors showed that Olig3 is predominantly required for the proper development of the earliest ventricular zone (VZ) and rhombic lip (RL) derivatives. They found that Olig3 regulates proliferation in the RL. Also, they showed that Olig3 acts cell-autonomously to prevent the misspecification of VZ-derived Purkinje cells (PCs) into inhibitory interneurons, by suppressing the expression of Pax2. Currently, the mechanisms that segregate different VZ and RL-derived lineages are poorly understood, and the implication of Olig3 in the segregation of PCs and inhibitory interneurons (with underlying mechanisms) is the most exciting part of this paper. As a whole, the paper makes a very valuable addition to our understanding of the mechanisms of cerebellar development.</p><p>In general, the experimental analysis is well done, and most conclusions are supported by strong experimental data. However, there are several cases of the over-interpretation of findings, which need to be addressed by additional analysis, more accurate discussion, and/or by providing better images.</p><p>1) Please provide higher magnification images (insets) to better appreciate the presence of cells double-positive for TdTomato/Brn2 and TdTomato/Tbr1 (Figure 2D); and cells double-positive for b-gal/Pax6 (Figure 2E), b-gal/Foxp2 (Figure 2G), and b-gal/Tbr1 (Figure 2F), and the lack of b-gal and Pax2 overlap (Figure 2H).</p><p>2) Figure 3&#x2014;figure supplement 3C: based on the provided panels, it is hard to see a difference in the number of BrdU<sup>+</sup> cells in the RL of <italic>Olig3<sup>GFP/GFP</sup></italic> and control embryos (region 2 in the mutant versus region 2 in the control embryo). More representative images need to be shown.</p><p>3) Throughout the paper, the authors state that loss of Olig3 results in ectopic expression of Pax2 in the RL (for example in the Introduction and Results). However, both Figure 4C (boxed regions) and Figure 4&#x2014;figure supplement 1A (region 2) show area adjacent to the RL, not the RL itself. To conclude that loss of Olig3 induces ectopic Pax2 expression in the RL, the authors need to show a high magnification of the RL itself. To precisely determine RL limits, Pax2 staining needs to be combined with a RL marker, such as Atoh1 (Pax2/Atoh1 double labeling or at least Pax2 and Atoh1 labeling in adjacent sections).</p><p>Alternatively, the authors may remove their conclusion regarding Pax2 de-repression in the RL of Olig3 mutants and delete a related discussion of inhibitory interneurons as the default neuronal phenotype (Discussion).</p><p>4) Figure 4C: It is hard to see whether in Olig3 mutant (the lower right high magnification image) Pax2+ cells co-express Foxp2. Single channel images are needed in addition to the already presented overlayed (red+blue channels together) image.</p><p>5) (Results and Discussion). The authors conclude that "Pax2.&#x2026; imposes an inhibitory interneuron fate". However, in this paper it is only shown that Pax2 inhibits Foxp2 (PC fate). To conclude that Pax2 is sufficient to impose an inhibitory interneuron fate, additional markers of mature interneurons need to be analyzed in Pax2-electroporated cells (in embryos in utero electroporated with a Pax2 expressing vector). Alternatively, authors can delete the statement about Pax2 imposing interneuronal fate and simply state that Pax2 is sufficient to suppress PC (Foxp2) identity.</p><p>6) It needs to be discussed that granule cell defects may be secondary to PC defects in Olig3 mutants rather than result from a direct role of Olig3 in the development of granule cell lineage.</p><p><italic>Reviewer #2:</italic></p><p>I don't have any further suggestions for this well-done study.</p><p><italic>Reviewer #3:</italic></p><p>In this study, the authors identify Olig3 among bHLH transcription factors expressed in the rhombic lip of the developing cerebellum using data from the Allen Developing Mouse Brain Atlas. They then use histology and IHC with quantitation, fate mapping, and in utero electroporation in wildtype and mutant mice to evaluate the role of Olig3 in early cerebellar development. They show Olig3+ cells in RL and VZ, the two progenitor zones that give rise to glutamatergic and GABAergic cells, respectively. Lineage tracing using <italic>Olig3<sup>creERT2</sup></italic> with Ai14 or TaunLacZ confirmed Olig3+ progenitors give rise to early cells that arise from the RL and VZ. Olig3 KO mice had a small, minimally foliated cerebellar vermis at birth. Most cell types were reduced in number consistent with overall hypoplasia, but Pax2+ cells were increased in number. The authors confirmed Olig3 absence leads to a fate change in cells emanating from the VZ with forced overexpression of Olig3 leading to Olig3+/Pax2+ cells. The further confirm that Olig2 does not compensate for this phenotype.</p><p>This study newly identifies Olig3 as an important determinant of early cerebellar cell types emanating from the RL and VZ. This paper is well written, methods are sound, and the Results and Discussion present the relationship to prior studies.</p><p>1) How was the list of bHLH transcription factors compiled? Does 108 represent ALL bHLH or only the subset that have data available in the Allen atlas? Are there additional bHLH that are not available in Allen? Please provide additional details. E.g. To orient the reader, it would be helpful to provide examples of the Allen gene expression for one gene that represents each category listed in Table 1/Figure 1A.</p><p>2) How are RL and VZ defined in this study? There are no anatomic boundaries that delineate these transient, three dimensional structures; how were boundaries determined? Please provide details for how these regions were identified (e.g. Atoh1+, PMID: 16202705) and quantified.</p><p>3) The Olig3+/Sox2Sox2<sup>+</sup> double positive yellow cells are difficult to see in Figure 1C. Showing an image as in Figure 1E could help the reader to visually correlate the quantitation of the double positive cells.</p><p>4) In the Discussion the authors state that Olig3 loss reduces the number of Atoh1+ cells. However, no expression of Atoh1 in Olig3 KO is shown to support this conclusion. The majority of Olig3+ RL cells do not express Atoh1 (Figure 1D). It is not clear from the data shown that Olig3 KO specifically affects Atoh1+ cells in the RL. Lmx1a is another gene critical for RL progenitor generation that is not co-expressed with Atoh1 (e.g. PMID: 204098) and Lmx1a/Olig3 coexpression was not evaluated; it's plausible that the other 2/3 of the Olig3+ RL cells coexpress Lmx1a.</p></sub-article><sub-article article-type="reply" id="sa2"><front-stub><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7554/eLife.64501.sa2</article-id><title-group><article-title>Author response</article-title></title-group></front-stub><p>Essential revisions:</p><p>The reviewers have made suggestions on how to improve the clarity of specific figures. Please see below for details. In addition, there are a number of suggestions to improve the clarity of how the data are interpreted. Therefore, there are minor additional data analysis/experiments required and several instances of reworking the text.</p><p>Title:</p><p>Please consider revising the title. The use of "master regulator" in particular could be toned down. Perhaps "early" regulator may be more appropriate.</p><p>We have considered your suggestion regarding revising the title and replaced the world &#x201C;master&#x201D; with &#x201C;early&#x201D;. The title of our work now reads:</p><p>&#x201C;Olig3 regulates early cerebellar development&#x201D;.</p><p>Reviewer #1:</p><p>Lowenstein et al., describe the novel roles of Olig3 in cerebellar development. The authors showed that Olig3 is predominantly required for the proper development of the earliest ventricular zone (VZ) and rhombic lip (RL) derivatives. They found that Olig3 regulates proliferation in the RL. Also, they showed that Olig3 acts cell-autonomously to prevent the misspecification of VZ-derived Purkinje cells (PCs) into inhibitory interneurons, by suppressing the expression of Pax2. Currently, the mechanisms that segregate different VZ and RL-derived lineages are poorly understood, and the implication of Olig3 in the segregation of PCs and inhibitory interneurons (with underlying mechanisms) is the most exciting part of this paper. As a whole, the paper makes a very valuable addition to our understanding of the mechanisms of cerebellar development.</p><p>In general, the experimental analysis is well done, and most conclusions are supported by strong experimental data. However, there are several cases of the over-interpretation of findings, which need to be addressed by additional analysis, more accurate discussion, and/or by providing better images.</p><p>1) Please provide higher magnification images (insets) to better appreciate the presence of cells double-positive for TdTomato/Brn2 and TdTomato/Tbr1 (Figure 2D); and cells double-positive for b-gal/Pax6 (Figure 2E), b-gal/Foxp2 (Figure 2G), and b-gal/Tbr1 (Figure 2F), and the lack of b-gal and Pax2 overlap (Figure 2H).</p><p>We now provide magnifications for the suggested figures.</p><p>In addition, we provide similar magnifications in Figure 2&#x2014;figure supplement 1D and E.</p><p>2) Figure 3&#x2014;figure supplement 3C: based on the provided panels, it is hard to see a difference in the number of BrdU<sup>+</sup> cells in the RL of Olig3<sup>GFP/GFP</sup> and control embryos (region 2 in the mutant versus region 2 in the control embryo). More representative images need to be shown.</p><p>In the revised Figure 3&#x2014;figure supplement 3C we now provide more representative images with insets displaying BrdU signals.</p><p>3) Throughout the paper, the authors state that loss of Olig3 results in ectopic expression of Pax2 in the RL (for example in the Introduction and Results). However, both Figure 4C (boxed regions) and Figure 4&#x2014;figure supplement 1A (region 2) show area adjacent to the RL, not the RL itself. To conclude that loss of Olig3 induces ectopic Pax2 expression in the RL, the authors need to show a high magnification of the RL itself. To precisely determine RL limits, Pax2 staining needs to be combined with a RL marker, such as Atoh1 (Pax2/Atoh1 double labeling or at least Pax2 and Atoh1 labeling in adjacent sections).</p><p>Alternatively, the authors may remove their conclusion regarding Pax2 de-repression in the RL of Olig3 mutants and delete a related discussion of inhibitory interneurons as the default neuronal phenotype (Discussion).</p><p>Dr. Victor V. Chizhikov is right in that our data did not directly address the fact that Pax2 becomes de-repressed in the rhombic lip. Methodologically, we face the problem that our Atoh1 and Pax2 antibodies are both generated in rabbit, which prevented us from co-staining Olig3 mutant tissue with both antibodies to determine whether Atoh1+ cells (like Foxp2+ cells) might co-express Pax2 in Olig3 mutant mice. Consecutive sections separately stained with Pax2 and Atoh1 do show that Pax2+ cells locate inside the Atoh1 domain in Olig3 mutant mice. However, we now reason that this result alone cannot unambiguously define whether these cells indeed generate from the rhombic lip or whether these cells are generated from the ventricular zone and displaced into the rhombic lip. We therefore removed our conclusion that Pax2 becomes de-repressed in the rhombic lip of Olig3 mutant mice throughout the text.</p><p>4) Figure 4C: It is hard to see whether in Olig3 mutant (the lower right high magnification image) Pax2+ cells co-express Foxp2. Single channel images are needed in addition to the already presented overlayed (red+blue channels together) image.</p><p>We now provide a new figure, Figure 4&#x2014;figure supplement 1, illustrating additional examples of Pax2 and Foxp2 co-expression in control and Olig3 mutant mice, with magnifications and the display of single and merged fluorescent channels. We did not alter the original Figure 4C as the main point we want to show in this figure is the de-repression of Pax2 in GFP+ cells in <italic>Olig3<sup>GFP/GFP</sup></italic> mutant mice.</p><p>5) (Results and Discussion). The authors conclude that "Pax2.&#x2026; imposes an inhibitory interneuron fate". However, in this paper it is only shown that Pax2 inhibits Foxp2 (PC fate). To conclude that Pax2 is sufficient to impose an inhibitory interneuron fate, additional markers of mature interneurons need to be analyzed in Pax2-electroporated cells (in embryos in utero electroporated with a Pax2 expressing vector). Alternatively, authors can delete the statement about Pax2 imposing interneuronal fate and simply state that Pax2 is sufficient to suppress PC (Foxp2) identity.</p><p>Dr. Victor V. Chizhikov is right that our original data only showed the suppressive function of Pax2 on Foxp2 expression.</p><p>We stained the cerebella of wildtype mice at E14.5 and E15.5 with antibodies against classical markers of GABAergic cells such as Parvalbumin, Somatostatin, Calbindin, Claretinin, Gad67 and Gad65, and compared their expression against Foxp2 (that labels Purkinje cells). We found Parvalbumin as a candidate marker for newborn inhibitory interneurons as it i) does not colocalize with Foxp2, and ii) follows that same distribution and expression pattern as Pax2, at least during the analyzed ages. We co-stained control and Pax2-electroporated cells with Parvalbumin and found that about a third of the Pax2-electroporated cells co-express Parvalbumin, whereas control electroporated cells rarely do. We now add this data in Figure 5&#x2014;figure supplement 1 and in the Results section.</p><p>However, we modified our conclusion that Pax2 imposes an inhibitory interneuron fate, as we now reason that the most conclusive way to demonstrate this would be by analyzing the morphology and physiology of Pax2-electroporated cells in postnatal life, which is outside the scope of our present work.</p><p>We now conclude:</p><p>&#x201C;We conclude that Pax2 is an efficient suppressor of Foxp2 expression and that its expression seems to induce a differentiation program characteristic of inhibitory interneurons.&#x201D;</p><p>We also modified the heading of this this experimental Results section to say:</p><p>&#x201C;Olig3 cell-autonomously curtails Pax2 expression to secure Purkinje cell differentiation&#x201D;.</p><p>6) It needs to be discussed that granule cell defects may be secondary to PC defects in Olig3 mutants rather than result from a direct role of Olig3 in the development of granule cell lineage.</p><p>We thank the reviewer for this insight. We now discuss this as follows:</p><p>&#x201C;One should note, however, that the reduced numbers of granule cells in Olig3 mutant mice might be mainly independent of Olig3 and due to the reduction of instructive signals emanating from Purkinje cells, which are severely affected in these mutant mice. Indeed, available evidence shows that Purkinje cells regulate EGL proliferation and the differentiation of granule cells via sonic hedgehog signaling (Dahmane and Ruiz i Altaba, 1999; Wallace, 1999; Wechsler-Reya and Scott, 1999).&#x201D;</p><p>Reviewer #3:</p><p>In this study, the authors identify Olig3 among bHLH transcription factors expressed in the rhombic lip of the developing cerebellum using data from the Allen Developing Mouse Brain Atlas. They then use histology and IHC with quantitation, fate mapping, and in utero electroporation in wildtype and mutant mice to evaluate the role of Olig3 in early cerebellar development. They show Olig3+ cells in RL and VZ, the two progenitor zones that give rise to glutamatergic and GABAergic cells, respectively. Lineage tracing using Olig3<sup>creERT2</sup> with Ai14 or TaunLacZ confirmed Olig3+ progenitors give rise to early cells that arise from the RL and VZ. Olig3 KO mice had a small, minimally foliated cerebellar vermis at birth. Most cell types were reduced in number consistent with overall hypoplasia, but Pax2+ cells were increased in number. The authors confirmed Olig3 absence leads to a fate change in cells emanating from the VZ with forced overexpression of Olig3 leading to Olig3+/Pax2+ cells. The further confirm that Olig2 does not compensate for this phenotype.</p><p>This study newly identifies Olig3 as an important determinant of early cerebellar cell types emanating from the RL and VZ. This paper is well written, methods are sound, and the Results and Discussion present the relationship to prior studies.</p><p>1) How was the list of bHLH transcription factors compiled? Does 108 represent ALL bHLH or only the subset that have data available in the Allen atlas? Are there additional bHLH that are not available in Allen? Please provide additional details. E.g. To orient the reader, it would be helpful to provide examples of the Allen gene expression for one gene that represents each category listed in Table 1/Figure 1A.</p><p>Following the suggestion above we created a new figure, Figure 1&#x2014;figure supplement 1, to include examples from the Allen Developing Mouse Brain Atlas of two genes that represent each category listed in Table 1/Figure 1A.</p><p>The precise number of bHLH transcription factors expressed in humans as well as in other organisms is yet to be defined. Phylogenetic analyses suggest that humans express approximately 130 bHLH factors, whereas mice express about 117 (Skinner et al., 2010; Stevens et al., 2008). In this study, we used the 110 genes annotated in the Human Genome Organization (HuGO; https://www.genenames.org/data/genegroup/#!/group/420). In our original search on the Allen Developing Mouse Brain Atlas we found data for 108/110 of the HuGO annotated genes. The genes that were not found in our original search were Arntl and Mycl.</p><p>During the revision of our manuscript, we revisited the Allen Brain Atlas and found data for both genes. We now include them in our list and classify them as not expressed (Arntl) and generically expressed in cerebellar progenitor cells (Mycl). The following changes have been made in our revised manuscript:</p><p>i) In the Results, we describe the selection of the 110 bHLH factors that are annotated in HuGO and provide the link for the resource.</p><p>ii) In the Results, we adjust our original number of listed genes to include Arntl and Mycl1 according to their expression.</p><p>iii) Figure 1A has been modified from 108 genes to 110 genes.</p><p>iv) Table 1 now includes Arntl1 and Mycl.</p><p>2) How are RL and VZ defined in this study? There are no anatomic boundaries that delineate these transient, three dimensional structures; how were boundaries determined? Please provide details for how these regions were identified (e.g. Atoh1+, PMID: 16202705) and quantified.</p><p>We defined RL and VZ boundaries according to the expression of Atoh1 and Ptf1a, respectively. To help the reader to visualize these boundaries, we now provide a revised Figure 1&#x2014;figure supplement 2, in which panel B illustrates the expression of Olig3 together with Atoh1 and Ptf1a.</p><p>3) The Olig3+/Sox2Sox2<sup>+</sup> double positive yellow cells are difficult to see in Figure 1C. Showing an image as in Figure 1E could help the reader to visually correlate the quantitation of the double positive cells.</p><p>In our revised Figure 1C, we now show magnifications of the rhombic lip and ventricular zone. Furthermore, we now display the images of the ventricular zone similar to the image of Figure 1E. We also displayed the Sox2 signals in blue to improve the visualization of cells co-expressing Olig3 (displayed in red). We did not include insets for the rhombic lip, as we believe the colocalization is easy to distinguish in its current form.</p><p>4) In the Discussion the authors state that Olig3 loss reduces the number of Atoh1+ cells. However, no expression of Atoh1 in Olig3 KO is shown to support this conclusion. The majority of Olig3+ RL cells do not express Atoh1 (Figure 1D). It is not clear from the data shown that Olig3 KO specifically affects Atoh1+ cells in the RL. Lmx1a is another gene critical for RL progenitor generation that is not co-expressed with Atoh1 (e.g. PMID: 204098) and Lmx1a/Olig3 coexpression was not evaluated; it's plausible that the other 2/3 of the Olig3+ RL cells coexpress Lmx1a.</p><p>In our original Figure 3&#x2014;figure supplement 3A, we showed immunostaining and quantification of Atoh1+ cells in Olig3 KO mice at E11.5 and at E12.5. These data illustrated a reduction in the number of Atoh1+ cells in Olig3 KO mice. We now also provide insets in the original photographs without GFP to improve the visualization of Atoh1+ cells.</p><p>In this study we focused on the elucidation of bHLH transcription factors responsible for the generation of the distinct cerebellar neuron types and did not include homeodomain proteins such as Lmx1a. Following the observation of reviewer 3, we performed fluorescent in situ hybridization for Olig3 and Lmx1a transcripts. This shows that indeed both Olig3 and Lmx1a partially co-localize in the rhombic lip (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="sa2fig1">Author response image 1</xref>). The potential cooperativity and interaction between Olig3 and Lmx1a in development of early rhombic lip derivatives is out of the scope of this work and remains to be determined.</p><fig id="fig8" position="float"><graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="tiff" xlink:href="elife-64501-fig8.tif"/></fig></sub-article></article>