<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d1 20130915//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd"><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xml:lang="en" dtd-version="1.1d1" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">spref</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">REF</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Educational Reform</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title>REF</abbrev-journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1056-7879</issn><publisher><publisher-name>International Journal of Educational Reform</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Sage CA: Los Angeles, CA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">10.1177_1056787919841501</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1056787919841501</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group>  <article-title>Job Satisfaction and Teacher Turnover Intentions in Malawi: a Quantitative Assessment</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib corresp="yes" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kafumbu</surname><given-names>Fatsani Thomas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1-REF841501">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corresp1-REF841501"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1-REF841501"><label>1</label>Naming&#x2019;omba Community Day Secondary School, Lilongwe, Malawi</aff><author-notes>  <corresp id="corresp1-REF841501">Fatsani Thomas Kafumbu, Naming&#x2019;omba Community Day Secondary School, C/O P. O. Box 2120, Lilongwe, Malawi; <email xlink:href="mailto:ftkafumbu@gmail.com">ftkafumbu@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epreprint"><year>2022</year></pub-date><volume>00</volume><issue>0</issue><fpage>1</fpage><elocation-id>1056787919841501</elocation-id><history><date date-type="accepted"><day>01</day><month>01</month><year>1900</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x00A9; The Author(s) 2019</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license><license-p>sagepub.com/journals-permissions</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>This study aimed at uncovering the link between levels of job satisfaction with turnover intentions among teachers with the aim of broadening the knowledge base as regards teachers&#x2019; welfare in public secondary schools in Malawi. In the empirical investigation, a correlational-analytic design was used. The stratified random sample consisted of 120 secondary school teachers and it was found that most teachers had a moderate level of satisfaction with their work. Furthermore, it was found that job satisfaction among teachers was related to their turnover intentions and that demographics had a significant influence on this relationship except for school type.</p></abstract><kwd-group> <kwd>job satisfaction</kwd> <kwd>turnover intention</kwd> <kwd>teacher motivation</kwd> <kwd>education</kwd> </kwd-group><custom-meta-group/></article-meta></front><body><p>An important point of emphasis in education research over the past several decades has been the issue of teacher motivation and retention. Employee retention is an essential component for the efficient operation of an organization in a rapidly expanding global economy (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-REF841501">Luthans, 1998</xref>). Motivation and job satisfaction play a major role towards retention. Among several factors, the work environment has an essential role to play toward increased job satisfaction and motivation among its members (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15-REF841501">Luthans, 1998</xref>). Previous studies on organizational behavior have shown that employees&#x2019; intentions to stay in an organization are positively related to various gains and<xref ref-type="chart" rid="CH4">Chart 4</xref> investment outcomes acquired during employment that cannot be transferred to another job (Becker, as cited in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr3-REF841501">Boyd, Grossman, Lankford, Loeb, &#x0026; Wyckoff, 2009</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-REF841501">Drukpa, 2010</xref>; Lachman &#x0026; Diamant, 1987). Such a relationship is evidently portrayed in the quality of education in the developing world which has been affected by diminishing quality due to, among other factors, high teacher attrition and dissatisfaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-REF841501">Cha, 2008</xref>).</p><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="fig1-REF841501"><label>Chart 4.</label><caption><p>sample chart caption</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="/resources/sage/ref/1056787919841501/resources/7be3e780-7ac1-41d3-9cdf-b326b6a1936d.png.JPEG"/></fig><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="fig2-REF841501"><label>Chart 5.</label><caption><p>sample chart caption</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="/resources/sage/ref/1056787919841501/resources/d48e71d5-f693-4e2a-867a-39e6cd5d0f87.jpeg.JPEG"/></fig><p>Low levels of teacher motivation and job satisfaction have been issues of public debate in Malawi over the past two decades (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23-REF841501">Ng&#x2019;ambi, 2010</xref>). Issues of stress and poor working conditions have been attributed to increased teacher turn-over rates in Malawi. This is evidenced by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14-REF841501">Kayuni and Tambulasi (2007)</xref> which shows that 1,121, out of 2,253 trained secondary school teachers, enrolled between January and June 2005 left their jobs or moved to non-teaching jobs. In more recent years, the number of resignations of secondary school teachers has been on a steady increase. For instance, in the years 2013 to 2014 the Southern Region of Malawi (which encompasses four Education Divisions) lost 215 teachers out a total of 4,323 (5 percent) and 359 teachers out of 5,943 (6 percent), respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-REF841501">EMIS, 2014</xref>). With the consistent inadequacy of manpower in the secondary subsector, there is a retrogressive effect on the system. Therefore, it is important to examine turnover intentions among secondary school teachers in Malawi in order to have a better understanding of their levels of job satisfaction. This would in turn provide proof for reference in coming up with future staff retention strategies for the education sector.</p><p>The objectives of this study were firstly to explore the level of job satisfaction among secondary school teachers in Malawi. Secondly, to identify the work-related factors which teachers are satisfied with. Lastly, to determine the influence of the level of job satisfaction on turnover intentions among secondary school teachers in the Shire Highlands Education Division in the Southern region of Malawi.</p><sec id="sec1-REF841501"><title>Literature Review</title><p>Researchers in the field of education have attributed several factors as influencing teachers&#x2019; job satisfaction which in turn leads to motivation towards turnover or retention in the school setting. Job satisfaction is one of the most researched, and written-about concepts by scholars and researchers in the field of leadership and management. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-REF841501">Perie &#x0026; Baker, 1997, July</xref> define job satisfaction as an emotional reaction to one&#x2019;s work situation with respect to work outcomes. Therefore the benefits accumulated by the employee from the organization would be expected to result in job satisfaction. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27-REF841501">Parvin and Kabir (2011)</xref> add on to describe job satisfaction as the level of contentment an individual has over his or her job. That is, the happier one is with their job the more satisfied they are with their job.</p><sec id="sec2-REF841501"><title>Theories of Motivation and Job Satisfaction</title><p>In one area of organizational theory, motivation, which refers to &#x201C;the reasons underlying behavior&#x201D; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10-REF841501">Guay et al., 2010</xref>, p. 712), has the strongest influence over job satisfaction (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26-REF841501">Pardee, 1990</xref>). Thus, in order to understand better the concept of job satisfaction, theories of motivation have an essential role to play. This section therefore presents the related literature on the concept of job satisfaction through the lens of some theories of motivation that include: Maslow&#x2019;s Hierarchy of Needs, Expectancy theory, and Herzberg two-factor theory.</p><sec id="sec3-REF841501"><title>Maslow&#x2019;s hierarchy of needs</title><p>The concept of job satisfaction in closely related to needs gratification. A noted in the definitions of job satisfaction, it is combination of cognitive and behavioral elements which interact within an individual. Maslow&#x2019;s Hierarchy of Needs, developed by Abraham Maslow, assumes that people have a variety of motivational needs and that these can be arranged hierarchically according to the order in which they are satisfied (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25-REF841501">Okumbe, 1998</xref>). Maslow assumed that motivation is as a result of the need to satisfy unmet needs. Maslow arranged such needs hierarchically indicating that individuals&#x2019; needs at any level on the hierarchy emerge only when lower level needs are reasonably satisfied. This trend according to Maslow&#x2019;s assumption is that as the person satisfies a lower-level need, the next higher need in the hierarchy becomes the primary motivator &#x2013; a concept referred to as satisfaction-progression process (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22-REF841501">Mullins, 2002</xref>). The needs hierarchy ranges from physiological, security, social to self-actualization needs.</p></sec><sec id="sec4-REF841501"><title>Expectancy theory</title><p>Vroom&#x2019;s expectancy theory of motivation is another relative model of job satisfaction. This theory was developed by Victor Vroom in 1964 and he argues that individuals make choices based on how well the expected results of a given behavior are going to match up with or eventually lead to the desired results (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-REF841501">Droar, 2006</xref>). In other words, people&#x2019;s expectations are encouraged by knowledge of the means, likelihood of achievement, and attractiveness of the reward. Individual expectations are usually biased by personal feelings (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr7-REF841501">Droar, 2006</xref>).</p><p>Vroom&#x2019;s theory is based on the equation of three factors referred to as: Expectancy, Instrumentality, and Valence. Expectancy refers to the strength of a person&#x2019;s belief about whether or not a particular job performance is attainable (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-REF841501">Bandura, 1986</xref>). Instrumentality refers to a person&#x2019;s belief that good performance will be rewarded by a valued outcome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-REF841501">Bandura, 1986</xref>). The term valence refers to the emotional orientations which people hold with respect to outcomes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr1-REF841501">Bandura, 1986</xref>).</p><p>With regard to motivating factors in a job such as income, it can be argued that if an employee highly values money after completing a job &#x2013; referred to as valence (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-REF841501">Holdford &#x0026; Lovelace-Elmore, 2001</xref>) &#x2013; the worker will likely want to go to work. However, this also depends upon the expectancy &#x2013; belief of attainability<xref ref-type="chart" rid="CH6">Chart 6</xref> of prize &#x2013; and instrumentality &#x2013; belief that prize will follow a job well done (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13-REF841501">Holdford &#x0026; Lovelace-Elmore, 2001</xref>). This theory suggests that &#x201C;job satisfaction is derived from both personality and situational variables&#x201D; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-REF841501">Drukpa, 2010</xref>).</p><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="fig3-REF841501"><label>Chart 6.</label><caption><p>sample chart caption</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="/resources/sage/ref/1056787919841501/resources/15274d0d-2eb3-4553-af01-a134cac6e863.png.JPEG"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec5-REF841501"><title>Herzberg&#x2019;s two-factor theory</title><p>Herzberg&#x2019;s Two-factor theory suggests that there are factors at work in the work environment that cause job satisfaction while a separate set of factors cause job dissatisfaction. These are referred to as motivational and hygiene factors.</p><p>According to the two factor theory, the motivators are the intrinsic contents of a job. According to Herzberg, individuals look for the gratification of these factors which are of higher order psychological needs. Examples of motivators include achievement, recognition, responsibility, and the nature of the work itself. It can be noted that these are factors that are directly related to work. As noted by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-REF841501">Drukpa (2010)</xref>, these are factors that have a stronghold over the personal emotion towards the job thereby producing job satisfaction. Motivators<xref ref-type="chart" rid="CH6">Chart 6</xref> towards satisfaction are acquired from achievement, recognition, work itself, responsibility and advancement (Herzberg, 1976). Hygiene factors, on the other hand, are those factors in a workplace that lead to job dissatisfaction. Such factors are extrinsic &#x2013; related to context of work &#x2013; and include status, job security, salary, fringe benefits, supervision, interpersonal relations, and working conditions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-REF841501">Ramadhani, 2014</xref>).</p><p>According to Herzberg (1976), these factors are of lower -order needs and they contribute very little to job satisfaction and if not met, they lead to job dissatisfaction. Herzberg argues that hygiene factors cannot motivate an individual, and when used to achieve this goal it can actually produce unwarranted effects in the long term. A "hygienic" environment prevents discontent with a job, but such an environment<xref ref-type="chart" rid="CH4 CH5 CH6">Charts 4&#x2013;6</xref> cannot lead the individual beyond a minimal adjustment consisting of the absence of dissatisfaction. A positive "happiness" seems to require some attainment of psycho-logical growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12-REF841501">Herzberg, 1966</xref>).</p><p>As noted by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-REF841501">Drukpa (2010)</xref> this is why Herzberg&#x2019;s theory is often criticized. In view of factors such as salary, critics are of the view that this can be both a motivator and a hygiene factor. Furthermore, individual differences and preferences are noted to have been omitted in this theory with more emphasis going to pleasure as an outcome (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-REF841501">Drukpa, 2010</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec6-REF841501"><title>Job Satisfaction and Turnover</title><p>Teacher turnover has for some time been an issue of concern among policy makers and other stakeholders in education as it &#x201C;represents instability in the teaching force and raises the prospect of shortage of qualified replacement teachers&#x201D; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-REF841501">Boe, Bobbitt, Cook, Whitener, &#x0026; Weber, 1997</xref>, p. 390). As noted by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-REF841501">Medina, 2012</xref>, research reveals that the job satisfaction-turnover relationship is moderated by employee intentions. That is to say, actual turnover is nothing other than the result of intentions held by the employee which later mature into actual turnover. According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33-REF841501">Simon, M&#x00FC;ller, and Hasselhorn (2010)</xref> turnover intention is simply defined as a measurement of whether employees of an organization plan to leave their jobs.</p><p>Due to employees&#x2019; interaction with several factors of the work environment which affects job satisfaction, numerous studies have discovered a positive relationship between job satisfaction and turnover (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32-REF841501">Schwepker, 2001</xref>). Occupational factors play an important role in influencing turnover among employees. O&#x2019;Brien, Goddard and Keeffe (2007), for example, found that exhaustion due to workload caused 29% of new teachers to start thinking about leaving teaching and 10% indicating that they had already made the decision to leave by their second year on the job. However, Manuel (as cited in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr4-REF841501">Buchanan et al., 2013</xref>, p. 113) argues that such findings cannot be generalized because &#x201C;not all beginning teachers experience the kind of hardship that leads to a decision to leave the profession&#x201D;. Similarly, various studies have found that there is a strong relationship between turnover and experience, with the least and most experienced teachers most likely to leave their schools (Murnane, et al., 1991).</p><p>The relationship between job satisfaction and turnover has been generally accepted in most job satisfaction literature. As noted by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-REF841501">Medina (2012)</xref>, the understanding of this relationship is key to understanding organizational behavior. Thus, in order to study the element of turnover among employees, most researchers have sought to use intentions as an alternative indicator.</p><p>The element of commitment to work has been linked by several studies to employees&#x2019; turnover intentions. Randal and Riegel in Tella (2007) define organizational commitment in terms of three dimensions, one of which is &#x201C;a strong desire to remain a member of a particular organization&#x201D;. Researchers have found that workers with the strongest level of commitment to the organization have the least intention to leave (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17-REF841501">Mathieu &#x0026; Zajac, 1990</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19-REF841501">Meyer &#x0026; Allen, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-REF841501">Meyer, Stanley, Herscovitch, &#x0026; Topolnytsky, 2002</xref>). In the study by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20-REF841501">Meyer et al., (2002)</xref> is was found that, in relation to commitment levels, turnover intentions were actually higher than actual turnover among workers.</p><p>Apart from commitment, role conflict is another factor that has been found to relate to turnover intentions among employees. Role conflict is defined in terms of the element of compatibility which is judged based on a set of standards or conditions which impinge upon role performance (Rizzo et al., 1970). According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr6-REF841501">Drenth (2009)</xref>, role conflict seems to have a large positive effect on turnover intention. That is to say, employees who experience role conflict have a higher intention to leave the organization than people who do not experience role conflict.</p><p>In order to understand the turnover intentions, researchers have observed the possible causes which are highly related to work itself. Lachman and Diamant (1987), in their seminal study, argue that some intention to leave one&#x2019;s job can be reduced by an employee&#x2019;s affective reaction to the work environment and restrained by expected gains from the current job. That is to say, formal or informal standing, assumption of roles, duties and school responsibilities may be a kind of investment which influences an employee&#x2019;s intent to stay or leave. According to the <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-REF841501">Cha (2008)</xref>, if teachers feel that their return is being lowered as they work, they will be less likely to invest in training and thus leave. Therefore, teachers who perceive that they have put too much into teaching but have not gotten enough in return may decide to leave.</p><p>The element of satisfaction of such factors, therefore, is seen to play an important role in determining an employee&#x2019;s intentions, either to stay or to leave. In agreement to this, Lachman and Diamant (1987), found that teachers' turnover intentions are affected by both withdrawal and restraining factors in the work environment, which should be used in explaining such intentions. The researchers further suggest accounting for demographic variables such as sex in future studies.</p></sec><sec id="sec7-REF841501"><title>Factors Affecting Job Satisfaction and Turnover</title><p>There are several factors that affect job satisfaction. Studies have shown that teachers&#x2019; job satisfaction, like any other white-collar profession is influenced by intrinsic and extrinsic factors. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-REF841501">Perie &#x0026; Baker, 1997, July</xref> explain that &#x201C;intrinsic factors may play a role in motivating individuals to enter the teaching profession, since most teachers enter the profession because they enjoy teaching and want to work with young people&#x201D;. On the other hand extrinsic factors of satisfaction, including salary, perceived support from administrators, school safety, and availability of school resources have also been noted to play a role in teacher satisfaction (Bobbitt et al.,; Choy et al., as cited in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28-REF841501">Perie &#x0026; Baker, 1997, July</xref>).</p><sec id="sec8-REF841501"><title>Work-related factors</title><p>There are a wide variety of work-related factor that affect job satisfaction. In the present study, work-related factors refer to working conditions, income, policy and management, promotion and advancement as well as workload. Understanding the effect of work-related factors can prove beneficial to the smooth operation of an organization as noted by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31-REF841501">Saleem, Majeed, and Aziz (2013)</xref> that a good salary package, work environment and chances to prospect in the future, may positively influence the employee&#x2019;s loyalty and ultimately increased job satisfaction.</p></sec><sec id="sec9-REF841501"><title>Demographic factors</title><p>Research on teacher turn-over and job satisfaction has tended to focus on teachers' characteristics, such as demographics, qualifications, and experience to determine those that are most likely to leave the job (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-REF841501">Boe et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-REF841501">Medina, 2012</xref>; Ngimbudzi, 2009). Demographic factors such as age, gender, experience and qualification cannot be ignored in studies on organizational behavior since worker are always in contact and cannot be detached from such factors. The connection between some demographic factors and job satisfaction has been found to be positive and sometimes negative (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16-REF841501">Mason, 1997</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec10-REF841501"><title>Purpose of the Study</title><p>The purpose of the study was to explore the level of job satisfaction among secondary school teachers in Malawi. This study tried to identify the work-related factors which teachers are satisfied with. Moreover, it tried to determine the influence of the level of job satisfaction on turnover intentions among secondary school teachers in the Shire Highlands Education Division.</p></sec><sec id="sec11-REF841501"><title>Research Questions</title><p>The research sought to respond to the following questions:</p><list list-type="roman-lower"><list-item><p>How satisfied are secondary school teachers with the overall aspects of their work?</p></list-item><list-item><p>What is the relationship between teachers&#x2019; level of job satisfaction (with working conditions, policy and management, income, promotion and advancement, and workload) and turnover intentions?</p></list-item><list-item><p>Do demographic variables (such as age, gender, qualification, work experience, and school type) influence the relationship between teachers&#x2019; job satisfaction and turnover intentions?</p></list-item></list></sec><sec id="sec12-REF841501"><title>Research Problem</title><p>To this end, the following research problem was identified:</p><disp-quote><p>To what extent does job satisfaction with various aspect of the work environment and demographics impact on turnover intentions among public secondary school teachers in Malawi.</p></disp-quote></sec><sec id="sec13-REF841501"><title>Conceptual Framework</title></sec><sec id="sec14-REF841501"><title>Hypothesis</title><p>From the above literature review the following hypotheses have been developed.</p><disp-quote><p><bold><italic>H1:</italic></bold> <italic>There is a significant relationship between teachers&#x2019; level of job satisfaction (with working conditions, policy and management, income, promotion and advancement, and workload) and turnover intentions.</italic></p><p><bold><italic>H2:</italic></bold> <italic>There is a significant influence of demographic variables (such as age, sex, qualification, work experience, and school type) on the relationship between teachers&#x2019; job satisfaction and turnover intentions.</italic></p></disp-quote></sec></sec><sec id="sec15-REF841501"><title>Research Design Methodology</title><sec id="sec16-REF841501"><title>Population &#x0026; Sample Size</title><p>The population of this study comprised of teachers from five Conventional Secondary Schools (CSSs) and five Community Day Secondary Schools (CDSSs) in the Districts of Mulanje and Thyolo located in the Southern Region of Malawi. The Southern Region is divided into three education divisions namely Shire Highlands Education Division (SHED), South West Education Division (SWED) and South East Education Division (SEED). However, for the purpose of this study, only teachers in the SHED were studied. According to the EMIS (2014) the SHED encompasses 114 public secondary schools (77 CDSSs, 27 CSSs, and 15 open schools) with a total of 3, 875 teachers. Therefore the population of the research was 3, 875 teachers in secondary schools in SHED. Therefore working from the population of 3, 875 with confidence level at 95 percent and Margin of Error of 8.8 percent, the sample size was 120 secondary school teachers from the SHED.</p></sec><sec id="sec17-REF841501"><title>Data Collection Methodology</title><p>The survey instrument used in this study was, therefore, a modified 5-point Likert scale questionnaire which was developed from studies by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-REF841501">Drukpa (2010)</xref>, and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-REF841501">Medina (2012)</xref>. The questionnaire was made up of three main sections. Section one consisted of questions related to personal and demographic factors such as age, gender, educational qualification, work experience, and school type. Section two of the survey instrument was made up of job satisfaction aspects. Levels of job satisfaction were measured through a 5-point Likert Scale (i.e., 1 = Not Satisfied, 2 = Least Satisfied, 3 = Somewhat Satisfied, 4 = Satisfied and 5 = Very Satisfied). Participants were required to indicate their level of satisfaction with the variables such as working conditions, policy and management, income, promotion and advancement, and workload.</p></sec><sec id="sec18-REF841501"><title>Classification of Means Equation</title><p>The level of satisfaction was determined through the classification of the scores from the responses which were classified into five levels of Best&#x2019;s criteria (as cited in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr8-REF841501">Drukpa, 2010</xref>) in the following way:</p><p>Equation 1: Best's criteria for classification of means</p><p id="E1"><disp-formula id="disp-formula1-1056787919841501"><label>(1)</label><alternatives><mml:math display="block" id="math1-1056787919841501"><mml:mrow><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>g</mml:mi><mml:mi>h</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x00A0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x00A0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x00A0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x00A0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>w</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x00A0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x00A0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x00A0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x00A0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mi>u</mml:mi><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x00A0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>f</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x00A0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>v</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x00A0;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x00A0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>i</mml:mi><mml:mi>k</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x00A0;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mrow><mml:mn>5</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x2212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mn>4</mml:mn><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:mfrac><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.8</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="../resources/sage/ref/1056787919841501/resources/1553080561572_cropped.png" specific-use="disp-formula1-1056787919841501"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p>Therefore, where 0.8 represents the range of mean scores per level of satisfaction, mean scores were interpreted as follows: 1.00 to 1.80 = not satisfied, 1.81 to 2.60 = least satisfied, 2.61 to 3.40 = somewhat satisfied, 3.41 to 4.20 = satisfied, 4.21 to 5.00 = very satisfied</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec19-REF841501"><title>Data Analysis</title><p>For data analysis purpose SPSS-19 version were used and following technique used were Cronbach&#x2019;s alpha, Correlation, and Descriptive statistics (mean, standard deviation).</p><sec id="sec20-REF841501"><title>Cronbach&#x2019;s Alpha</title><p>Internal reliability of the instrument was checked by using Cronbach&#x2019;s alpha. The standard value of reliability is 0.7 and results indicate the value of 0.79 which is above of the standard value 0.7 and thus is reliable.</p></sec><sec id="sec21-REF841501"><title>Demographic Characteristics of the Sample Population</title><p>The data generated indicated that, in general, there are a notably lower number of female teachers as compared to their male counterparts in public secondary schools. The survey revealed that of the 120 respondents interviewed, 78.3% were male while 21.7% were female (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig5-REF841501">Figure 2</xref>). This is reflective of the continuing gender disparities in the secondary education subsector where the majority of teaching staff are largely male.</p><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="fig4-REF841501"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Conceptual framework.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="/resources/sage/ref/1056787919841501/resources/c94ac868-b25b-41c6-9fd3-af253f8c2eb0.tif.JPEG"/></fig><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="fig5-REF841501"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Demographics of sample population.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="/resources/sage/ref/1056787919841501/resources/acb2e341-30cb-4eef-89ab-3c7add07c79d.tif.JPEG"/></fig><p>With regard to age difference among the surveyed participants, the data revealed that the majority of the teachers were between the age range of 30 to 49 and 40 to 49. That is, participants in both age ranges registered an equal percentage of 35.8. The high number of young professional in the system paints a picture of a possible increase in the number of new graduates entering the teaching profession over the past few years. The oldest group (of 50 years or older) in the population sampled fell at a minimal 10%.</p><p>Since the study involved teachers teaching in Conventional Secondary Schools (CSSs) and Community Day Secondary Schools (CDSSs), the data generated revealed that the sample consisted of 47.5% of teachers teaching in CSSs and teachers in CDSSs at 52.5%. As would be expected, this is reflective of the fewer number of CSSs as opposed to CDSSs in Malawi. As presented in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr9-REF841501">EMIS (2014)</xref>, CSSs only cover 23.7% of the total number of secondary schools in SHED.</p><p>Forty-five percent (45%) of the teachers sampled were university graduates with a Bachelor&#x2019;s degree. On the other hand, 44.2% of the teachers sampled were diploma holders. This implies that most secondary schools have a good number of qualified teachers as noted by Ministry of Education Science and Technology (2014) that the Student Qualified Teacher Ratio has improved from the previous 70:1 to 46:1 from the year 2009 to 2012. Apart from this, it can also be noted that the results of the introduction of the mode of upgrading under-qualified teachers to Diploma level through the distance education model and University Certificate of Education (UCE) have been reflected in these findings. However, the data showed that only 3.3% of the teachers had a postgraduate qualification.</p><p>Teaching experience was another factor for which the participants were supposed to provide data. It was revealed that the majority of the teachers surveyed, 30% had a maximum of 5 years&#x2019; experience and these were trailed by 22.5% of teachers who had 6 to 10 years&#x2019; experience. In was further noted that 19.2% of the teachers interviewed had 16 or more years of experience. Such figures reveal that there is a substantial number of experienced teachers in secondary schools in SHED. It further reveals the growing number of new teachers in the secondary subsectors which is in fact showing achievement of priority 2 (quality and relevance) of the National Education Sector Plan by recruiting trained teachers in secondary schools (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21-REF841501">MoEST, 2008</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec22-REF841501"><title>Descriptive Statistics</title><p><xref ref-type="table" rid="table1-REF841501">Table 1</xref> shows descriptive data of job satisfaction of teachers in SHED presented through means and standard deviations which were calculated from the 46 items from which the different job satisfaction facets were divided. From the analysis, it is revealed that the majority of teachers were &#x2018;somewhat satisfied&#x2019; with their job as shown by the overall average mean score of 2.62 with a standard deviation of .84. A closer look at the analytical data revealed that teachers&#x2019; level of satisfaction differed according to each job satisfaction facet. As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig6-REF841501">Figure 3</xref>, participants were least satisfied with income which had an average mean of 2.04 and standard deviation of .88, as well as promotion and advancement (a motivator) which had a mean of 2.29 and standard deviation of .84. On the other hand, teachers showed higher levels of satisfaction with their working conditions (a hygiene factor), policy and management (hygiene factors) as well as workload (a motivator).</p><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="fig6-REF841501"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Mean levels of satisfaction among teachers by job satisfaction aspects.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="/resources/sage/ref/1056787919841501/resources/dbd260b8-4f27-48ed-b57e-70dd03539cb6.tif.JPEG"/></fig><table-wrap position="float" id="table1-REF841501"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Job Satisfaction of Teachers in SHED (n = 120)</p></caption><alternatives><graphic specific-use="table1-1056787919841501" xlink:href="10.1177_1056787919841501-table1.tif"/><table frame="hsides"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom">Satisfaction facet</th><th align="center" valign="bottom">Mean</th><th align="center" valign="bottom">Std. deviation</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Working Conditions</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">2.93</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">.72</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Policy and Management</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">2.88</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">.91</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Income</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">2.04</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">.88</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Promotion and Advancement</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">2.29</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">.84</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Workload</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">2.94</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">.83</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Average of all means and Std. Deviation</td><td align="center" valign="bottom"><bold>2.62</bold></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">.<bold>84</bold></td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-fn1-1-REF841501"><p><italic>Note</italic>. 1.00&#x2013;1.80 = not satisfied, 1.81&#x2013;2.60 = least satisfied, 2.61&#x2013;3.40 = somewhat satisfied, 3.41&#x2013;4.20 = satisfied, 4.21&#x2013;5.00 = very satisfied.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec23-REF841501"><title>Bivariate Correlation Analysis</title><p>Correlational analysis, bivariate (two-way) statistics using Pearson&#x2019;s product moment correlation coefficient was used to find out whether any relationships existed between working conditions and turnover intentions and summarized results are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="table2-REF841501">Table 2</xref> below:</p><table-wrap position="float" id="table2-REF841501"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Summarized Results of Bivariate Correlation Analyses</p></caption><alternatives><graphic specific-use="table2-1056787919841501" xlink:href="10.1177_1056787919841501-table2.tif"/><table frame="hsides"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom" colspan="2"/><th align="center" valign="bottom">Turnover intentions</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="3">Working Conditions</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">Pearson Correlation</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">&#x2212;.280<sup>**</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">Sig. (2-tailed)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">.002</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">N</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">120</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="3">Policy and Management</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">Pearson Correlation</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">&#x2212;.419<sup>**</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">Sig. (2-tailed)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">.000</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">N</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">120</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="3">Income</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">Pearson Correlation</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">&#x2212;.480<sup>**</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">Sig. (2-tailed)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">.000</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">N</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">120</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="3">Promotion and Advancement</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">Pearson Correlation</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">&#x2212;.392<sup>**</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">Sig. (2-tailed)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">.000</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">N</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">120</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom" rowspan="3">Workload</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">Pearson Correlation</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">&#x2212;.397<sup>**</sup></td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">Sig. (2-tailed)</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">.000</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="bottom">N</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">120</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>Hypothesis H1 is accepted because using correlational bivariate analysis, it was determined that:</p><list list-type="roman-upper"><list-item><p>There was a significant linear relationship between the teachers&#x2019; level of satisfaction with working conditions and turnover intentions (<italic>r</italic> (118) =&#x2212;.280, <italic>n =</italic> 120<italic>, p</italic> = .002, 2-tailed);</p></list-item><list-item><p>There was a moderate, negative (statistically significant) correlation between policy and management and turnover intentions, <italic>r (118) =&#x2212;</italic>.419, <italic>n</italic> = 120<italic>, p</italic> &#x003C; .001 (2-tailed);</p></list-item><list-item><p>Income and turnover intentions showed a statistically significant linear relationship where <italic>r</italic> (118) <italic>=&#x2212;</italic>.480, <italic>n</italic> = 120<italic>, p</italic> &#x003C; .001 (2-tailed);</p></list-item><list-item><p>Promotion and Advancement and turnover intentions showed statistically significant relationship <italic>, r (118) =&#x2212;</italic>.392, <italic>n</italic> = 120<italic>, p</italic> &#x003C; .001 (2-tailed); and</p></list-item><list-item><p>Workload and turnover intentions relationship showed was statistically significant<italic>, r (118) =&#x2212;</italic>.397, <italic>N</italic> = 120<italic>, p</italic> &#x003C; .001 (2-tailed).</p></list-item></list><p>The findings show that teachers who had a higher level of satisfaction with working conditions, policy and management, promotion and advancement and workload tended to have lower turnover intentions. On the other hand, teachers who had lower levels of satisfaction tended to have high turnover intentions.</p></sec><sec id="sec24-REF841501"><title>Partial Correlation Analysis</title><p>First, to determine whether there was a linear relationship between the two variables, a scatter plot was created. The overall job satisfaction, which was determined from the average means of each job satisfaction facet, was used as the independent variable. As presented in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig7-REF841501">Figure 4</xref>, there was a linear relationship between job satisfaction and turnover intentions.</p><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="fig7-REF841501"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Scatter plot of overall job satisfaction and turnover intentions.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="/resources/sage/ref/1056787919841501/resources/999b8e43-53ad-4eff-8aba-8cefc86fc87b.tif.JPEG"/></fig><p>Partial correlation was run to determine the relationship between job satisfaction and turnover intentions whilst controlling for the demographic variables of age gender, qualification, work experience, and school type. The summarized results of the findings (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table3-REF841501">Table 3</xref>) were as follows:</p><table-wrap position="float" id="table3-REF841501"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Partial Correlations Among Job Satisfaction and Turnover Intentions Controlling for Age, Gender, Qualification, Work Experience, and School Type</p></caption><alternatives><graphic specific-use="table3-1056787919841501" xlink:href="10.1177_1056787919841501-table3.tif"/><table frame="hsides"><thead><tr><th align="left" valign="bottom">Control variables</th><th align="center" valign="bottom">R value</th><th align="center" valign="bottom">Df</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Age</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">r (118) =&#x2212;.505</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">117</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">-None-</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">r (117) =&#x2212;.498</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">118</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Gender</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">r (118) =&#x2212;.505</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">117</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">-None-</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">r (117) =&#x2212;.496</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">118</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Qualification</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">(r (118) =&#x2212;.505</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">117</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">-None-</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">r (117) =&#x2212;.496</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">118</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Experience</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">r (118) =&#x2212;.438</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">117</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">-None-</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">r (117) =&#x2212;.499</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">118</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">School type</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">r (118) =&#x2212;.505</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">117</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">-None-</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">r (117) =&#x2212;.515</td><td align="center" valign="bottom">118</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p>There is a moderate, negative correlation between job satisfaction and turnover intentions, which was statistically significant, <italic>r</italic> (117) =&#x2212;.498, <italic>n =</italic> 120, <italic>p &#x003C;</italic> .001. However, zero-order correlations showed that there was a statistically significant, strong and negative correlation between job satisfaction and turnover intentions (<italic>r</italic> (118) =&#x2212;.505, <italic>n =</italic> 120, <italic>p</italic> &#x003C; .001). This indicates that age had an influence in controlling for the relationship between job satisfaction and turnover intentions.</p></list-item><list-item><p>There is a moderate, negative relationship between job satisfaction and turnover intentions, which was statistically significant, <italic>r</italic> (117) =&#x2212;.496, <italic>n =</italic> 120, <italic>p &#x003C;</italic> .001. However, when we refer to the Pearson&#x2019;s product-moment correlation (zero-order correlation) between job satisfaction and turnover intentions, without controlling for gender, there was also a statistically significant, strong and negative correlation between the two variables (<italic>r</italic> (118) =&#x2212;.505, <italic>n =</italic> 120, <italic>p</italic> &#x003C; .001). This suggests that gender influences the relationship between job satisfaction and turnover intentions.</p></list-item><list-item><p>In determining whether educational qualification has any significant influence on the relation between the two variables, the results show that there is a moderate, negative relationship. This relationship is statistically significant, <italic>r</italic> (117) =&#x2212;.496, <italic>n =</italic> 120, <italic>p &#x003C;</italic> .001. On the other hand, zero-order (Pearson) correlation between the two variables also shows a moderate, negative statistically significant relationship (<italic>r</italic> (118) =&#x2212;.505, <italic>n =</italic> 120, <italic>p &#x003C;</italic> .001. This proposes that educational qualification has an influence on the job satisfaction and turnover intentions relationship.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The analysis revealed the existence of a moderate, negative relationship between the two variables (r (117) =&#x2212;.499, <italic>n</italic> = 120, <italic>p</italic> &#x003C; .001) while controlling for work experience. On the other hand, the zero-order (Pearson) correlation between the same two variables, shows a strong, negative statistically significant relationship (<italic>r</italic> (118) =&#x2212;.438, <italic>n =</italic> 120, <italic>p &#x003C;</italic> .001. A comparison of this data suggests that work experience has an influence on the job satisfaction and turnover intentions relationship.</p></list-item><list-item><p>There was a moderate, negative correlation between job satisfaction and turnover intentions, which was statistically significant, <italic>r</italic> (117) =&#x2212;.515, <italic>n =</italic> 120, <italic>p &#x003C;</italic> .001. On the other hand, zero-order correlations also showed that there was a statistically significant, moderate and negative correlation between job satisfaction and turnover intentions (<italic>r</italic> (118) = &#x2212;505, <italic>n =</italic> 120, <italic>p</italic> &#x003C; .001), indicating that school type had very little influence in controlling for the relationship between job satisfaction and turnover intentions.</p></list-item></list><p>The research findings revealed that there is a significant influence of demographic variables (age, gender, qualification, work experience) on the relationship between teachers&#x2019; job satisfaction and turnover intentions. However, this is with the exception of school type which was found to indeed have no significant influence on the relationship.</p><p>The findings are in agreement with research done by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr2-REF841501">Boe et al., (1997)</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18-REF841501">Medina (2012)</xref> and Ngimbudzi (2009) who focus on demographic factors as determinants of teacher turnover. Results are also consistent with the findings of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-REF841501">Ramadhani (2014)</xref> who found that job satisfaction and demographic variables contribute 75 percent to the employees&#x2019; turnover intentions. However, the results of the research disagree with the findings of Lankford, Loeb, and Wyckoff cited in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr5-REF841501">Cha (2008)</xref> and <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11-REF841501">Hanushek, Kain, and Rivkin (1999)</xref> who found that type of school played a role in determining teacher turnover. It is my assumption that the difference in results is mainly as a result of the difference in the population under study. Since the presented study was conducted in the Malawian context, there are prone to be differences with other studies. Nevertheless, there is need for research to determine the extent to which differences in school type would cause teacher turnover. Further analysis reveals that on the gender aspect contradicts the findings of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29-REF841501">Ramadhani (2014)</xref> who found that gender and education have no significant role to employees&#x2019; turnover intentions. Based on the results, the hypothesis H2 was rejected.</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec25-REF841501"><title>Conclusions and Implications</title><p>The purpose of the study was to explore the relationship between job satisfaction and turnover intentions among secondary school teachers in the Shire Highlands Education Division (SHED) in the Southern Region of Malawi.</p><p>Descriptive statistics as shown by the overall average mean score of 2.62 with a standard deviation of .84 on satisfaction level revealed that teachers in SHED are quite satisfied with their work. Teachers were found to be most satisfied with their working conditions, policy and management as well as workload. However, lower satisfaction was with promotion and advancement which had a mean of 2.04 and standard deviation of .88. This implies the need for head teachers in collaboration with MoEST to put in place proper monitoring and evaluation mechanisms to ensure fairness of career progression systems. On the other hand, the results propose that the current public opinion which suggests that secondary school teachers are unsatisfied with their work is generally false as this mostly emanates from the consideration of income which is not the only factor that ensures satisfaction in the work place. However, it appears that income is a major factor of influence among secondary school teachers in SHED. By implication, the findings propose the need for key policy makers in the Ministry of Education, Science and Technology to work towards finding a sustainable solution towards improving teachers&#x2019; satisfaction as regards their income.</p><p>Using Bivariate Correlation analysis, results indicated that there was a statistically significant relationship between teachers&#x2019; turnover intentions and their level of satisfaction with working conditions, policy and management, income, promotion and advancement, and workload. The relationship was strongest in relation to income, and policy and management which suggest a high level of influence of such job satisfaction facets on teachers&#x2019; work life. By implication, the results suggest that policy makers at all levels in the secondary education subsector need to pay special attention to issues affecting teachers, particularly the improvement of job satisfaction characteristics (especially income, and policy and management) which can work as a staff retention strategy. These findings which indicate a close relationship between income and level of job satisfaction are partially consistentPhoto 1 with Herzberg&#x2019;s (1966) theory which views income (salary) as a hygiene(Photo 1) factor which if not satisfied can lead to dissatisfaction in the work place.</p><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="fig8-REF841501"><label>Photo 1.</label><caption/><graphic xlink:href="/resources/sage/ref/1056787919841501/resources/625b0451-084f-4681-ab4b-c9cf8887edd1.JPEG.JPEG"/></fig><p>The research findings also reveal that secondary school teachers in SHED are least satisfied with the amount of opportunities they have for promotion. In most cases teachers have low levels of job satisfaction and would likely (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-REF841501">Scheme 1</xref>)  jump at an opportunity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig9-REF841501">Scheme 1</xref>)  for a better job. The results imply the need for policy makers to review the policy on how teachers are and should be promoted if possible teacher turnover is to be averted.</p><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="fig9-REF841501"><label>Scheme 1</label><caption/><graphic xlink:href="/resources/sage/ref/1056787919841501/resources/bb0db617-0e69-4ee1-a233-eac2a128e7c7.png.JPEG"/></fig><p>The study findings also revealed that secondary schools are constrained in terms of human resources as most teachers were least satisfied with the chances of attending to individual students for tutoring. This explains the high pupil-teacher ratios which are prevalent in most secondary schools especially in rural areas, a characteristic held by most CDSSs and CSSs in SHED. This implies that policy makers need to come (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig10-REF841501">Scheme 2</xref>)  up with a sustainable strategy of ensuring the increased supply and retention of teachers in rural secondary schools which would be beneficial for an increased internal efficiency of the secondary subsector.</p><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="fig10-REF841501"><label>Scheme 2</label><caption/><graphic xlink:href="/resources/sage/ref/1056787919841501/resources/8a069c4b-20e0-4a9b-84c3-e7c8847fde3d.png.JPEG"/></fig><p>Partial correlation analysis revealed that there was a significant influence of demographic variables such as age, gender, qualification, and work experience on the relationship between teachers&#x2019; job satisfaction and turnover intentions. On the effect of school type which was seen to have no effect on the job satisfaction and turnover intension relationship, the researcher is of the view that the geographical location of the schools sampled, which was mostly rural, might have had an effect on the results of the study as regards the influence of school type on the relationship between job satisfaction and turnover(<xref ref-type="graph" rid="GH1">Graph 1</xref>) intentions. Thus, the results<xref ref-type="graph" rid="GH2">Graph 2</xref> reveal that demographic factors can determine the level of job satisfaction or turnover intentions among teachers. This implies the need for policy makers at the Ministry of Education, Science and Technology, and school administrators to take into account such demographic(<xref ref-type="graph" rid="GH1">Graph 1</xref>) variables whenever they look into issues of job satisfaction and staff retention in secondary schools.</p><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="fig11-REF841501"><label>Graph 1.</label><caption/><graphic xlink:href="/resources/sage/ref/1056787919841501/resources/a14d34c2-dbe7-44da-9371-b53980ba4020.JPEG.JPEG"/></fig><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="fig12-REF841501"><label>Graph 2.</label><caption/><graphic xlink:href="/resources/sage/ref/1056787919841501/resources/d767aa5a-b23e-4b94-b25b-83dccacd2fe3.jpg.JPEG"/></fig><sec id="sec26-REF841501"><title>Suggestions for Further Research</title><p>The research findings are not conclusive in the study of job satisfaction and turn over intentions among secondary school teachers in the(<xref ref-type="chart" rid="CH1">Chart 1</xref>) Malawian context(Photo 2) and thus the need for continued research. Therefore, the following suggestions for further research are made:</p><list list-type="simple"><list-item><p>The present study was strictly quantitative in nature. It is therefore suggested that future studies on the same topic employ mixed methods, that is, both qualitative and quantitative methods which would bring a wider perspective on the issue under study.</p></list-item><list-item><p>This empirical study used data gathered from teachers in secondary schools under the Shire Highlands Education Division which are mostly in rural areas. A similar study can be conducted on teachers in schools located in urban areas for a comparative analysis.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The current study explored the effect of demographic<xref ref-type="chart" rid="CH2">Chart 2</xref> variables on the job satisfaction and turnover intentions relationship. A comparative study could be conducted in order to investigate the extent of the influence of each demographic factor so as to note the essential factors to consider in research.</p></list-item><list-item><p>The present study was correlational and this implies that its results cannot be used conclusively to predict future turnover of teachers. It therefore would be of value if future research would employ regression analysis in order to investigate if a cause-effect relationship exists between job satisfaction and turnover intentions among teachers in Malawian public secondary schools.</p></list-item></list><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="fig13-REF841501"><label>Photo 2.</label><caption/><graphic xlink:href="/resources/sage/ref/1056787919841501/resources/45c98904-c338-455a-8ab3-cb6d0f819e7c.png.JPEG"/></fig><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="fig14-REF841501"><label>Chart 2.</label><caption/><graphic xlink:href="/resources/sage/ref/1056787919841501/resources/af0c3008-3269-4039-8da7-b0a1dd3bbd29.jpg.JPEG"/></fig><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="fig15-REF841501"><label>Chart 1.</label><caption/><graphic xlink:href="/resources/sage/ref/1056787919841501/resources/627823e9-f22d-4764-80de-adf420ebf63c.JPEG.JPEG"/></fig><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="fig16-REF841501"><label>Uncited Chart 3.</label><caption><p>sample chart caption</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="/resources/sage/ref/1056787919841501/resources/058caba4-6874-432d-b8dc-7db022df6be0.png.JPEG"/></fig><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="fig17-REF841501"><label>Uncited Chart 7.</label><caption><p>sample chart caption</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="/resources/sage/ref/1056787919841501/resources/fbac30a4-434d-4fe9-b746-db01b4b99689.png.JPEG"/></fig><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="fig18-REF841501"><label>Uncited Chart 8.</label><caption><p>sample chart caption</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="/resources/sage/ref/1056787919841501/resources/522ccbbf-9d57-4aee-b654-15816bc8ce01.png.JPEG"/></fig><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="fig19-REF841501"><label>Uncited Chart 9.</label><caption><p>sample chart caption</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="/resources/sage/ref/1056787919841501/resources/524b8ceb-3d58-45b5-ba05-848c15924f03.png.JPEG"/></fig><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="fig20-REF841501"><label>Uncited Chart 11.</label><caption><p>sample chart caption</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="/resources/sage/ref/1056787919841501/resources/62892689-b961-472e-9ebb-8bed2469ff9d.png.JPEG"/></fig></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" specific-use="figshare" id="sec27-REF841501"><title>Supplemental Material</title><supplementary-material xlink:href="/resources/sage/ref/1056787919841501/resources/7ecbd612-8973-47ca-b1b7-c90e9e1b4b97.JPEG" mimetype="image/jpeg" id="suppl1-REF841501"><caption><title>Uncited online supplementary file 1 - Supplemental material for Job Satisfaction and Teacher Turnover Intentions in Malawi: a Quantitative Assessment</title></caption><p>Supplemental material, Uncited online supplementary file 1, for Job Satisfaction and Teacher Turnover Intentions in Malawi: a Quantitative Assessment by  and Fatsani Thomas Kafumbu in International Journal of Educational Reform</p></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><app-group><app id="A1"><sec id="sec28-REF841501"><title>APPENDIX 1</title><p>Test appendix content - added by sabari</p><fig position="float" fig-type="figure" id="fig21-REF841501"><label>Uncited Appendix 1Chart 1.</label><caption><p>sample chart caption</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="/resources/sage/ref/1056787919841501/resources/ab5f1469-5879-4d25-8a4d-584d6ff39a4f.png.JPEG"/></fig></sec></app></app-group><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"> <label>Declaration of Conflicting Interests</label><p>The author(s) declared no potential conflicts of interest with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p> </fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><label>Funding</label><p>The author(s) received no financial support for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group><fn fn-type="supplementary-material"><label>Supplemental Material</label><p>Supplemental material for this article is available online.</p></fn></fn-group><bio><title>Author Biography</title><p><bold>Fatsani Thomas Kafumbu</bold> is an educationist with over 8 years of experience as a teacher and administrator. He holds a Master Education (Policy, Planning and Leadership) degree from the University of Malawi and is an experienced researcher in public policy and an author. He currently works for the Ministry of Education, Science and Technology in Malawi and his interests lie in Education Policy, Planning and Organizational Psychology.</p><p>Email: <email>ftkafumbu@gmail.com</email></p></bio><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="bibr1-REF841501"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bandura</surname> <given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>1986</year>). <source>Social foundation of thought and action: A social cognitive theory</source>. <publisher-loc>New Jersey</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Prentice- Hall</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr2-REF841501"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boe</surname> <given-names>E. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bobbitt</surname> <given-names>S. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cook</surname> <given-names>L. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitener</surname> <given-names>S. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname> <given-names>A. L</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Why Didst thou go? predictors of retention, transfer, and attrition of special and general education teachers from a national perspective</article-title>. <source>The Journal of Special Education</source>, <volume>30</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>390</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>411</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/002246699703000403">doi:10.1177/002246699703000403</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr3-REF841501"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boyd</surname> <given-names>D. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grossman</surname> <given-names>P. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lankford</surname> <given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Loeb</surname> <given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wyckoff</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Teacher preparation and student achievement</article-title>. <source>Educational Evaluation and Policy Analysis</source>, <volume>31</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>416</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>440</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.3102/0162373709353129">doi:10.3102/0162373709353129</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr4-REF841501"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buchanan</surname> <given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prescott</surname> <given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schuck</surname> <given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aubusson</surname> <given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Burke</surname> <given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Louviere</surname> <given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Teacher retention and attrition: Views of early career teachers</article-title>. <source>Australian Journal of Teacher Education</source>, <volume>38</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>112</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>129</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.14221/ajte.2013v38n3.9">doi:10.14221/ajte.2013v38n3.9</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr5-REF841501"><mixed-citation publication-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cha</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Explaining teachers' job satisfaction, intent to leave, and actual turnover: a structural equation modeling approach</article-title>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://fsu.digital.flvc.org/islandora/object/fsu:182180/datastream/PDF/view">https://fsu.digital.flvc.org/islandora/object/fsu:182180/datastream/PDF/view</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr6-REF841501"><mixed-citation publication-type="thesis"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drenth</surname> <given-names>J. C</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>The ingredients for a committed workforce (MBA thesis), (unpublished doctoral dissertation or master's thesis). University of Twente, the Netherlands</article-title>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr7-REF841501"><mixed-citation publication-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Droar</surname> <given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Expectancy theory of motivation</article-title>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.arrod.co.uk/archive/concept_vroom.php">http://www.arrod.co.uk/archive/concept_vroom.php</ext-link>. (Accessed <date-in-citation>August 2014</date-in-citation>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr8-REF841501"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drukpa</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>2010</year>). <source>Job satisfaction of secondary school teachers in Thimphu District of Bhutan. Unpublished Master&#x2019;s thesis</source>. <publisher-loc>Thailand</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Mahidol University</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr9-REF841501"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group><collab>EMIS</collab></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <source>Education statistics 2014</source>. <publisher-loc>Lilongwe</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>EMIS</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr10-REF841501"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guay</surname> <given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chanal</surname> <given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ratelle</surname> <given-names>C. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marsh</surname> <given-names>H. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Larose</surname> <given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boivin</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Intrinsic, identified, and controlled types of motivation for school subjects in young elementary school children</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Educational Psychology</source>, <volume>80</volume>(<issue>4</issue>), <fpage>711</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>735</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1348/000709910X499084">doi:10.1348/000709910X499084</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr11-REF841501"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hanushek</surname> <given-names>E. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kain</surname> <given-names>J. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rivkin</surname> <given-names>S. G</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>1999</year>). <source>Do higher salaries buy better teachers?</source> <publisher-loc><italic>Cambridge, MA</italic></publisher-loc>: <publisher-name><italic>National Bureau of Economic Research</italic></publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr12-REF841501"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Herzberg</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>1966</year>). <source>Work and the nature of man</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Thomas Y. Crowell Co</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr13-REF841501"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holdford</surname> <given-names>D. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lovelace-Elmore</surname> <given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Applying the principles of human motivation to pharmaceutical education</article-title>. <source>J Pharm Teach</source>, <fpage>8 </fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>18</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr14-REF841501"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kayuni</surname> <given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tambulasi</surname> <given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Teacher turnover in Malawi&#x201F;s Ministry of education: Realities and challenges</article-title>. <source>International Education Journal</source>, <volume>8</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>89</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>99</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr15-REF841501"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luthans</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>1998</year>). <source>Organisational behaviour</source> (<edition>8th ed</edition>). <publisher-loc>Boston, MA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Irwin McGraw-Hill</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr16-REF841501"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mason</surname> <given-names>E. S</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>A case study of gender differences in job satisfaction subsequent to implementation of an employment equity programme</article-title>. <source>British Journal of Management</source>, <volume>8</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>163</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>173</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/1467-8551.0048">doi:10.1111/1467-8551.0048</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr17-REF841501"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mathieu</surname> <given-names>J. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zajac</surname> <given-names>D. M</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>A review and meta-analysis of the antecedents, correlates, and consequences of organizational commitment</article-title>. <source>Psychological Bulletin</source>, <volume>108</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>171</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>194</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1037/0033-2909.108.2.171">doi:10.1037/0033-2909.108.2.171</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr18-REF841501"><mixed-citation publication-type="thesis"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Medina</surname> <given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Job satisfaction and employee turnover intention: what does organizational culture have to do with it? (Master&#x2019;s thesis). </article-title><publisher-loc>Columbia University</publisher-loc>, <publisher-name>USA</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr19-REF841501"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meyer</surname> <given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Allen</surname> <given-names>N. J</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>A three-component conceptualization of organizational commitment</article-title>. <source>Human Resource Management Review</source>, <volume>1</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>61</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>89</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/1053-4822(91)90011-Z">doi:10.1016/1053-4822(91)90011-Z</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr20-REF841501"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meyer</surname> <given-names>J. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanley</surname> <given-names>D. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Herscovitch</surname> <given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Topolnytsky</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Affective, continuance, and normative commitment to the organization: A meta-analysis of antecedents, correlates, and consequences</article-title>. <source>Journal of Vocational Behavior</source>, <volume>61</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>20</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>52</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1006/jvbe.2001.1842">doi:10.1006/jvbe.2001.1842</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr21-REF841501"><mixed-citation publication-type="web"><person-group><collab>MoEST</collab></person-group>. (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>National education sector plan</article-title>. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://planipolis.iiep.unesco.org">http://planipolis.iiep.unesco.org</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr22-REF841501"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mullins</surname> <given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>2002</year>). <source>Management and organisational behaviour</source>. <publisher-loc>Englewood Cliffs</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Prentice Hall FT</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr23-REF841501"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ng&#x2019;ambi</surname> <given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>2010</year>). <source>Malawi: Effective delivery of public education services</source>. <publisher-loc>Johannesburg</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Open Society Initiative for Southern Africa</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr24-REF841501"><mixed-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O'Brien</surname> <given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goddard</surname> <given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Keeffe</surname> <given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>2008</year>). &#x201C;<article-title>Burnout confirmed as a viable explanation for beginning teacher attrition</article-title>&#x201D; <conf-name>Australian Association for Research in Education Annual Conference 2007: Research Impacts: Proving or Improving?</conf-name> <conf-loc>Fremantle: Western Australia</conf-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr25-REF841501"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Okumbe</surname> <given-names>J. A</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>1998</year>). <source>Educational management: theory and practice</source>. <publisher-loc>Nairobi</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Nairobi University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr26-REF841501"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pardee</surname> <given-names>R. L</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>1990</year>). <article-title>Motivation theories of Maslow, Herzberg, McGregor &#x0026; McClelland. A literature review of selected theories dealing with job satisfaction and motivation</article-title>. <source>Educational Resources Information Center</source>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr27-REF841501"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parvin</surname> <given-names>M. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kabir</surname> <given-names>M. M. N</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Factors affecting employee job satisfaction of pharmaceutical sector</article-title>. <source>Australian Journal of Business and Management Research</source>, <volume>1</volume>(<issue>9</issue>), <fpage>113</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>123</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr28-REF841501"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perie</surname> <given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname> <given-names>D. P</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>1997</year>, Jul). <source>Job Satisfaction among America&#x2019;s teachers: Effects of workplace conditions, background characteristics, and teacher compensation (Report)</source>. <publisher-loc>UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Center for Education Statistics</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr29-REF841501"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramadhani</surname> <given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <source>Factors influencing job satisfaction and turnover intentions in commercial banks (Master&#x2019;s thesis</source>. <publisher-loc>Tanzania</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Open University of Tanzania</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr30-REF841501"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rizzo</surname> <given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>House</surname> <given-names>R. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lirtzman</surname> <given-names>S. I</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>1970</year>). <article-title>Role conflict and ambiguity in complex organizations</article-title>. <source>Administrative Science Quarterly</source>, <volume>15</volume>(<issue>2</issue>), <fpage>150</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>163</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.2307/2391486">doi:10.2307/2391486</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr31-REF841501"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saleem</surname> <given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Majeed</surname> <given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aziz</surname> <given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Determinants of job satisfaction among employees of banking industry at Bahawalpur</article-title>. <source>Journal of Emerging Issues in Economics, Finance and Banking</source>, <volume>1</volume>(<issue>2</issue>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr32-REF841501"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schwepker</surname> <given-names>C. H</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>Ethical climate's relationship to job satisfaction, organizational commitment, and turnover intention in the salesforce</article-title>. <source>Journal of Business Research</source>, <volume>54</volume>(<issue>1</issue>), <fpage>39</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>52</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/S0148-2963(00)00125-9">doi:10.1016/S0148-2963(00)00125-9</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr33-REF841501"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Simon</surname> <given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x00FC;ller</surname> <given-names>B. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasselhorn</surname> <given-names>H. M</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Leaving the organization or the profession - a multilevel analysis of nurses' intentions</article-title>. <source>Journal of Advanced Nursing</source>, <volume>66</volume>(<issue>3</issue>), <fpage>616</fpage>&#x2013;<lpage>626</lpage>.<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2648.2009.05204.x">doi:10.1111/j.1365-2648.2009.05204.x</ext-link></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr34-REF841501"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tella</surname> <given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ayeni</surname> <given-names>C. O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Popoola</surname> <given-names>S. O</given-names></name></person-group>. (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Work motivation, job satisfaction, and organizational commitment of library personnel in academic and research libraries in Oyo state, Nigeria</article-title>. <source>Library philosophy and practice</source>, <volume>2007</volume>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>